<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Palladis palatium vvisedoms pallace. Or The fourth part of Wits commonwealth.</title>
            <author>Wrednot, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111763</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847033</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847033</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12040</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15745)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12040)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1018:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Palladis palatium vvisedoms pallace. Or The fourth part of Wits commonwealth.</title>
                  <author>Wrednot, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 128, 128-149, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by G. Elde for Francis Burton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Wrednot.</note>
                  <note>Number 4 in the "Wits" series.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Wisdoms pallace.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Aphorisms and apothegms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12040:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12040:1"/>
            <p>Palladis Palatium: WISEDOMS PALLACE. Or The fourth part of Wits Common-wealth.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mprinted by <hi>G. Elde</hi> for <hi>Francis Burton.</hi> 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:12040:2"/>
            <p>me, againe to preſent your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips with an other parcell of the ſame mans labours, in hope that you both will (as formerly you haue done) yeald a fauourable al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance vnto this worke, and alſo a kinde conſtruction of my rude, though well meaning, Epiſtle. The booke for argument contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth varietie of many excelent ſentences, collected out of the choiceſt writings of the auncient fathers. Here may wit finde plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and ſweete flowers to ſuck hunny from. Here may youth finde wholeſome precepts to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his future life. Here may the minde that readeth with an intention to profit, reape ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular commoditie. Here may the wearied and defatigate ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, recreate it ſelfe with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able delightes. Here may moſt
<pb facs="tcp:12040:2"/> (good) diſpoſitions light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome thinges to firte their deſires. And here I doubt not but both your worſhips ſhall finde much matter of content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when your leaſures will affoorde you time to peruſe it. I truſt that I neede not frame any Apologie in the defence or excuſe of the booke it ſelfe, for vertue is to bee loued for it owne ſake, and therefore I hope that the matter it ſelfe, will winne fauour vnto it ſelfe. If not, yet I knowe that, <hi>Vireſcit vnlnere virtus:</hi> Vertue if ſhe be wounded can heale it ſelfe, and will appeare by ſo much more glorious, by how much more eagerly vice en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoureth to dimme the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>Wherfore in ful perſwatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12040:3"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <hi>alas vertue is well neere baniſhed, vice hath almoſt gotten the vpper hand, wiſdome is derided of fooks, and the ſeeming-wiſe approue themſelues to be witleſſe, by their heedleſse courſes, for</hi> Exitus acta probat: <hi>the end tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the truth of the matter, &amp; the raſh conceipts of yong vnripe heads, are comptrouled by the approued experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of riper iudgments. Many are the excelent precepts which the works of the learned afford, and not few alſo are the idle fancies of vaine and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe heads. The latter ſort men much hunt after whereby they increaſe their follies, but the former ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is much neglected whereby wiſdomes reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not a little impaired. Let there be by ſtealth, or any other vnlawfull meanes, any idle Pamphlet, ſtuffed with more then villany, ſet to ſale (to corrupt vertuous minds) and it ſhall not want vtterance, for</hi> Nitimur in
<pb facs="tcp:12040:3"/> vetitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſemper cupimuſque negat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>But let there be many excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bookes of much worth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>piled, (if duly regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) yet if ſome, more then extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary matter be not therein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained, they may hap to lye by the walls. The conſideration wherof might eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage many good men from paines taking in that kinde, &amp; terrifie thoſe who vndertake the publiſhing therof, from aduenturing ſo far in a matter likely to proue ſo little to their aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. But yet hoping that the approued ſayings and experimented ſentences of the worthy authors herein contained, will be ſome ſtay vnto raſh-headed fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yeeld ſome content vnto wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms louers, in the peruſall hereof: as the Authour hath beſtowed his paines in colecting hereof, ſo haue I aduentured the Charges in Printing hereof, being hereunto the better incouraged by reaſon of the good
<pb facs="tcp:12040:4"/> ſucceſſe that this authors former booke entituled</hi> The ſorowfull Soules ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, or Teares of true repentance, ſhed for ſinne: <hi>hath already obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at his readers hands: Thus gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reader wiſhing that thou maieſt gaine double as much pleaſure in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing hereof, as the author did paynes in collecting hereof, I reſt thy friend and well-willer.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:12040:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A table of the principall</hi> heads contayned in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Abſtinence. page. 1.</item>
               <item>Abuſe. pag. 4.</item>
               <item>Acceptation of perſons. pag. 6.</item>
               <item>Aide. pag. 9.</item>
               <item>Anger. page. 12.</item>
               <item>Bleſſedneſſe. pag. 14.</item>
               <item>Benefits and benefitting. pag. 16.</item>
               <item>Blaſphemie. pag. 20.</item>
               <item>Bondage. pag. 21.</item>
               <item>Charitie. pag. 23.</item>
               <item>Chaſtitie &amp; continency. pag. 26.</item>
               <item>Coryection. pag. 29.</item>
               <item>Curioſity. pag. 31.</item>
               <item>Conuerſation. pag. 32.</item>
               <item>Diſcipline. pag. 34.</item>
               <item>Diſcord and Diſſention. pag. 35.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12040:5"/>
               <item>Delight and pleaſure. pag. 37.</item>
               <item>Deſperation. pag. 38.</item>
               <item>Detraction. pag. 39.</item>
               <item>Deuill. pag. 42.</item>
               <item>Enuie. pag. 44.</item>
               <item>Exerciſe. pag. 47.</item>
               <item>Excuſe. pag. 48.</item>
               <item>Example. pag. 52.</item>
               <item>Flattery. pag. 54.</item>
               <item>Fayth. pag. 57.</item>
               <item>Greefe. pag. 59.</item>
               <item>Guile and deceipt. pag. 62.</item>
               <item>Hereſie. pag. 64.</item>
               <item>Humilitie. pag. 66.</item>
               <item>Ignorance. pag. 68.</item>
               <item>Infirmitie. pag. 70.</item>
               <item>Iuſtice. pag. 71.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12040:5"/>
               <item>Knowledge or wiſdome. pag. 73.</item>
               <item>Learning. pag. 78.</item>
               <item>Liberalitie. pag. 81.</item>
               <item>Miſery. pag. 83.</item>
               <item>Mercie and pitty. pag. 86.</item>
               <item>Nature. pag 88.</item>
               <item>Necgligence. pag. 90.</item>
               <item>Nobility. pag. 91.</item>
               <item>Obedience. pag. 92.</item>
               <item>Obſtinancie. pag. 94.</item>
               <item>Order and degrees. pag. 95.</item>
               <item>Pouertie. pag. 97.</item>
               <item>Preaching. pag. 99.</item>
               <item>Quareling, ſtrife, &amp; contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 101.</item>
               <item>Quietnes, peace and tranquility of minde. pag. 104.</item>
            </list>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="collection">
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:12040:6"/>
                  <q>the ſwéetneſſe of trifling toyes, &amp; what a ioyfull thing is it vnto me now to let go thoſe things which before I feared to looſe? For thou (oh Lord) diddeſt caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of me, and thou, (oh chiefeſt ſwéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) diddeſt enter in their roomes: thou more ſwéete then all pleaſures, but not to fleſh and bloud: Thou that art more cleare then all light, more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward then any ſecret, and more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then all honors, but not to thoſe that are high in their owne conceits. <bibl>Aug. confeſſ.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Abſtinence is the mother of health, and pleaſure of ſickneſſe, for without meate and drinke luſt quickly ceaſeth. <bibl>Hierom. in his epiſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Moderate, and temperate meate, is commodious both to the ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. <bibl>Hierom. ad Ruſticum.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Great abſtinence is daingerous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tender, before they come vnto ripe age, <bibl>Idem ad latam.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Abſtinence, if it be ſo thou tame not the body as much as it can abeare, is no vertue: and it is very inordinate, if the body be brought lower then it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12040:6"/> ought. <bibl>Greg. lib. 20. mor.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Not the fleſh, but the vices thereof are through abſtinence to be extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: ſo it is neceſſary that euery one be ſo farre foorth continent as may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the vices, not the fleſh: for often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in purſuite of the enemie, therin, we kill the citizen whom we loue: and oftentimes alſo while we do, as it were ſpare our fellow Citizen, we further the enemie in the ſkirmiſh, <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The appetite and not the meate is faultie: for oftentimes we eate dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties without any fault finding: but we do diſtaſte thoſe meates that are more groſſe, without any féeling of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <bibl>Idem lib. 30. moral.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Nothing is ſo pleaſant as meate well digeſted and decocted: nothing ſo auaileable vnto health, nothing ſo much ſurthereth the ſharpneſſe of the ſences, nothing ſo much repelleth ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as moderate refection. For ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient not onely nouriſheth vs and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth health, but alſo begetteth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: But ſuperaboundance, or exceſſe cauſeth diſeaſes, bringeth moleſtations,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12040:7"/> a yonge man diſobedient: a rich man that will giue no almes: a woman that is vnchaſt: a maiſter without vertue: a contentious chriſtian: a poore man proud, an vnrighteous king: a negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Biſhop: a common wealth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcipline: and the people without lawe. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Acceptation of perſons.</head>
                  <q>GOD forbid that into the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, rich men ſhould be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before poore, or noble before them of lowe condition: when thou rather haſt choſen that with the weake thou ſhouldeſt confound the ſtrong. <bibl>Aguſti.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Greateſt is the offence of miniſters, becauſe they reſpect not the cauſes, but the perſons, and the iuſt poore man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſpiſed, the vniuſt rich men are honoured. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>In iudgment let not fauour beare ſway, but giue ſentence according to the equity of the cauſe. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is not conſanguinity, but the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12040:7"/> bond of vertue that linketh men toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The affection vrgeth vs to do many things: for whiles we regard the alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of our earthly bodies we often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times offend the creator both of bodies and ſoules. <bibl>Hierome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>To accept the perſon of a man, is not to honour him as he is a man, but for ſome other thing wherewith he is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Vniuſt iudges, while they conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the calling of men, do erre in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment yea very oftentimes the iudges themſelues doe corrupt the vpright when as they themſelues doe ſhamful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defende the guilty and vniuſt. <bibl>Iſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The acceptation of a mans perſon is a certaine ſlender reuerence or regard giuen vnto any one, not of deſert, but for feare or profit. <bibl>Cardinall Hugh.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Iudgment is eaſilie peruerted by the rich mans bribes: but a poore man wanting what to giue is not only<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> contemned, but alſo againſt equitie is oppreſſed. <bibl>Iſydore.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:12040:8"/>
                  <q>The perſons of men, not the iuſtneſſe of the cauſes are accepted: bribes not lawes are regarded: not what reaſon ſpeaketh, but what the will affecteth: not what the minde thinketh, but what the minde deſireth: not what is lawfull but what pleaſeth is regarded: nay the eye is neuer ſo ſingle, that the whole body may be light, but alwayes ſome leauen is mixed wherewith the whole lumpe is corrupted. <bibl>Innocentius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The poore mans cauſe is with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes neglected: &amp; the rich mans cauſe inſtantly proſecuted; To the poore all rigour is ſhewed, to the riche all cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſte vſed: the rich mens bad cauſes are hardly looked vnto, but the poore are charged with hainous crimes. The poore mans tale is negligently hard, but the rich mans words are highly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The poore man cryeth, and no man heareth: the rich man ſpeaketh &amp; euery one applaudeth: the rich man ſpeaketh and all men hould their peace, and his words are exhalted vnto the clouds: the poore man ſpeaketh, and they ſay,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12040:8"/> who is this man? and if he offend euer ſo little, he is quite ouerthrowne. To the rich they ſay: ſit downe here and reſt thée well: but to the poore they ſay, ſtand there, or els ſit at my foote-ſtoole. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Aide.</head>
                  <q>ALL men ought to be loued equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, but if thou be not of abilitie to profit all men, ſuccour thoſe eſpecially who by reaſon of the times or the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or by any other opportunities, are by a certaine lot vnited vnto thee. <bibl>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is vpright counſell, that if thou deſire to be holpen of thoſe that are thy betters, thou thy ſelfe ſhouldeſt yéelde ſuccour vnto thine inferiours.</q>
                  <q>A friend will beare his friends bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It was pretilie ſaid of a certaine man who falling into a Well was almoſt choaked with the water, and an other man comming vnto the Well wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſaid: how commeſt thou hither? I pray thée ſaid the man in the well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12040:9"/> thee of meanes to helpe me forth and aſke me not how I fell in. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Thoſe aides are not eaſily gotten in aduerſity which are not ſought for in proſperity. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>If one man cannot be holpen vnles another be hurt, it is better that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be profited then one hurt or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is impudent begging to require aide of him in neceſſity and trouble, whom in thy proſperity thou thy ſelfe contemnedſt.</q>
                  <q>It behoueth him to feare damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion who hauing liberty of ſpeache with the rich doth not make interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the poore as well as he can. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that may help, and yet doth not, maketh himſelfe a part-taker: he that furthereth anothers good ſetteth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward alſo his owne. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>To helpe the poore is a déede of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye, but to deſire the helps of the mightye is an argument of pride. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12040:9"/>To withdrawe ſomewhat from thine owne pleaſures and beſtowe it vpon thy brothers neceſſities, argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that there is a temperate meane in the loue that thou beareſt vnto thine owne ſelfe. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Do ſo for others that thou leaue not thine owne buſineſſe vndone, for wée are not bounde to profitt our freinds and hurt our owne ſelues. <bibl>Caſſ.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that denieth aide vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, thinketh that he needeth not the helpe of other men. <bibl>Lactantis.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is an extreame greefe to an honeſt man to be forced to helpe him whom to help he hath no delight. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is reaſon that he who in proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty holps others, ſhould in aduerſitie be holpen him ſelfe. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Whoſoeuer may ſaue ones life that is ready<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to periſh and yet doth not, is himſelfe guiltye of murder. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It thy friend fall into pouerty ſtudy to helpe him: nay rather (if thou canſt) to preuent his neede. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12040:10"/>In vaine dooſt thou ſéeke for aide of him of whom thou haſt deſerued to be puniſhed: as thou haſt done to others, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o expect that others ſhould doe vnto thée. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Anger.</head>
                  <q>AS Vineger if it remaine long multeth the veſſell, ſo anger if it continue vntill the morrow poiſoneth the heart. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The anger of a brother if it be inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate, is turned into hatred: Anger troubleth, hatred extinguiſheth: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is a moate, hatred is a great beame. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is angry, ſuppoſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be angry without a cauſe. <bibl>Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Reſiſt anger if thou canſt, if thou canſt not, giue place thereto: if An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhall preuent, and preoccupie thy minde, and ſhall ſeize vpon thée, leaue not thy place: thy place is patience. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is no meane thing to mittigate anger: it is no leſſe then not to be at all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12040:10"/> troubled in minde: this latter belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto our ſelues, the former vnto nature. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that is moued with himſelfe for being ſoone angry, ceaſeth to be angry with an other: but he that will iuſtifie his owne anger, is more inflamed, and ſoone offendeth. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is an excellent thing to temper the motion with councell: neither is it accounted leſſe vertuous to bridle thine anger, then not at all to be angry, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that for the moſt part this is eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the leſſe, the former the greater. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Praiſe-worthy is the ſaying of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitas</hi> of <hi>Tharectum,</hi> who being angry with his Bayliffe, ſaid: Now were I not moued with anger I would ſurely beate thée. <bibl>Hierome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Through anger a man becommeth ſo fooliſh, that he knoweth neither what to do, or in what order any thing ought to be done. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:12040:11"/>
               <head>B.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Bleſſedneſſe.</head>
                  <q>WRetched is the man who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things but thée (oh God.) But he that knoweth thée and all things els, is bleſſed, not for that be knoweth other things, but for the knowledge of thée alone. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Bleſſed are the vnſpotted in the way: as if it had béene ſaid, I know thy deſire: thou ſéekeſt happineſſe. If therefore thou deſire to be bleſſed, liue vnſpotted. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>That bleſſedneſſe is imperſect, of whoſe eternitie thou ſtandeſt in doubt. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He is not bleſſed who poſſeſſeth thoſe things that he deſireth, if be ſo his will be inclined vnto euill: But happy is he that obteincth all that he wiſheth, and wiſheth nothing vnbeſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming or euill. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Bleſſed is he who longeth not after thoſe things, which being enioyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come burthenſome: being beloued yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12040:11"/> doe defile: being loſt, doe vex and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a man. Is it not ſufficient with honour to deſpiſe thoſe things which thou parteſt from with griefe? <bibl>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Albeit all men are not a like exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon earth, yet their bliſſe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhall be alike: and the very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the fault ſhall be poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with that bleſſedneſſe, not which diſtaineth, but which tyeth vs more néerely vnto ioy. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Happy is he by whoſe height to his friends is giuen cauſe of ioy, to his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of griefe, to his poſteritie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, to the ſtrong and luſtie an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and vnto the ſlow and ſluggiſh allurements vnto vertue. <bibl>Caſſius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>That (vnleſſe I be deceiued) is true and perfect felicitie, which maketh a man ſufficient, mighty, reuerend, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and ioyfull: and (that thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt know that I haue déeply wayed it) which can perfectly performe euery one of theſe, (becauſe all things are the ſame) that I acknowledge to be true and perfect felicitie. <bibl>Boetius.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:12040:12"/>
                  <head>Benefits or Benefitting. <hi>The definition.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <q>A Benefit is a willing action of the minde, giuing and receiuing ioy, by beſtowing that which it doth. <bibl>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>In Gods ſight the hand is not emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a guift, if be ſo the coafer of the hart be full of good-will. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Thou oughteſt to giue that which may hurt neither thy ſelfe nor yet an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other man. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>No man doth well againſt his will, albeit that which he doe be of it owne ſelfe good. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Vertue knoweth no meaſure of thankeſgiuing: neither is contented to repay that which it hath receiued, but deſireth to requite double that which if hath taken. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>There is great difference betwéene the matter of a benefit, and the benefit it ſelfe: for neither ſiluer, nor gold, nor any other thing which we receiue of our friend, can be termed properly a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12040:12"/> benefit, but the benefit is the very af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and will of the giuer: But the ignorant only call that which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the benefit: An emperors crowne, apparell, and chariot, neither of theſe is properly honor, but the enſigne of honour: So likewiſe that which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to the ſight is not the benefit, but the ſigne of the benefit. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>There are many that will accept of no good turnes at an other mans hands becauſe they are vnwilling to do any good turnes to others them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</q>
                  <q>If contrary to thy expectation thou receaue a benefit, although the ſame (in value) be beſtowed on others alſo, yet is the benefit greater vnto thée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it came vnlcoked for.</q>
                  <q>This ought to be the lawe of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit betwéene two: he that conferreth it, ought preſently to forget it, but he vpon whem it is conferred ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to remember it. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Oftentimes it falleth out that thoſe things which are requeſted are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full if they be graunted, and therefore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12040:13"/> ired of thoſe from whom thou vniuſtly tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t, then goodwill of thoſe vnto whom thou vnwiſely giueſt. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is a very commendable thing to preuent the requeſt of an honeſt man by yéelding vnto his deſire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath altogether vttered his minde, for he will be halfe aſhamed to aſke, wheres a knaue in aſking wtil be impudent.</q>
                  <q>Nothing is more dearly bought then that which is by much intreatie obtained, for it is a heauie and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſaying, with a delected counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce to ſay, <hi>Sir I intreat you.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Many men will do a good turne vnto other, but it will be with ſuch frowning and angry woords that a man would repent him to haue obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a venefit at their hands.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Blaſphemie.</head>
                  <q>Their offences are as great who bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eme Chriſt r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> heauen, as ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>the ſinnes of thoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12040:13"/> who crucified him vpon the earth. <bibl>Auguſt ſuper ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It was a death vnto the Iewes, when they hearde any blaſphemie, to rent their clothes, as Paul and <hi>Barnabas</hi> when they ſhould be bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouted with diuine worſhip, rent their garments.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Bondage.</head>
                  <q>WHoſoeuer is diſmaid with feare, enſnared with delight, leo with luſt, exaſperated by anger, or oppreſſed with ſadneſſe, is in bondage: for euery paſſion is ſcruile, <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A good man although he be in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage is free, but an euil man although he be free yet is he in bondage. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Bondage is the obedience of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour aged minde, which wanted his owne iudgment. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>All bondage is miſerable, but to ſerue an vnhoneſt vnchaſte and effeminate perſon is vntollerable, and moſt wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Many men are in bondage, one to luſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12040:14"/> another to couetouſneſſe, a third to ambition, but moſt to feare. There is no bondage more diſhoneſt then that which is voluntarie. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Whoſoeuer is angry with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and is cruell withall, doth ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently demonſtrate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> he wanteth nothing but powre and abilitie againſt others alſo. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Whoſoeuer iudgeth that bondage happeneth vnto the whole man, erreth: for the body is bound vnto the will of the maiſter, but the minde is frée, and ſubiect to no humaine law: <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Behaue thy ſelfe chéerefully with ſhy ſeruants, not proudly, for they had rather reuerence thée as their better and ſuperior, then feare thée. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſhould haue béene ſold for a bond-ſlaue, and a certaine man who was willing to buy him, demanded of him what ſeruice he knew: who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering ſaid; I know how to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand freemen: wherefore he ſet him at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and deliuering vnto him his owne ſonnes, ſaid, take and rule theſe my children, <bibl>Aulus Gall.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12040:14"/>Art thou willing that thy fleſh ſhould ſerue thy ſoule? let thy ſoule ſerue God: before thou thy ſelfe gouerneſt, thou oughteſt to be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>No man can in one and the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame thing ſerue God and Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: for he which pleaſureth Gods enemie, ſheweth himſelfe a back-friend vnto God. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Many valiant men are oftentimes compelled to attend a whole day vpon an earthly iudge, when as yet God who is iudge of all, diſpatcheth thoſe that call vpon him ſeruently in the minute of an houre. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Charitie.</head>
                  <q>In Charitie a poore man may be rich, but without charitie all men are poore. <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Charitie is the roote of all goodneſſe, and couetouſneſſe the roote of all euill: both of which cannot be in one man,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12040:15"/> becauſe vnleſſe the one be rented out, the other cannot be planted: in vaine dooth he ſéeke to crop the boughes, which endeuoureth not to pull vp the roote. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Charitie ſédeth the hungry, ſo alſo doth pride: the one that God might be glorified, the other that it ſelfe might be praiſed. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Whatſoeuer hath charitie, neuer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth whereof to giue. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>I neuer remember that he dyed an euill death, which willingly exerciſed the workes of charitie: for he hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny interceſſors, and it is impoſſible that the prayers of many ſhould not be heard. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Euen as many boughes ſpréede out of one roote, ſo many vertues procéede out of Charitie only: neither hath the bough of good-worke any gréeneneſſe if it remaine not in the roote of charitie. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Stubberneſſe will not ſuffer vs to enter into other mens hearts, neither d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th ſuſpition ſuffer vs to beléeue that we are beloued of others: This double
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12040:15"/> diſeaſe is cured with a double charitie, to wit, that Charitie which ſéeketh not its owne, and that Charitie which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeueth all things. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Charity which is of God, is as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine forcible power of vertue, vnder which happy pleaſure buddeth, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly workes fructifie, it is in aduerſitie patient, in proſperitie temperate: migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in humilitie and ioyfull in affliction: wiſhing well vnto the bad, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming the euill with good. <bibl>Caſſiod.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>What (oh Charitie) can in praiſe of thée be more ſpoken then this that thou cauſedſt God to diſcend from heauen, and alſo man to aſcend from earth to heauen. Great I ſay is the veriye of thée, which cauſedſt God to humble himſelfe vnto the duſt, and raiſedſt men from duſt to heauen. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Charitie is the ſtrength of faith, and faith the bond of loue: and then is the name true, and the fruite of them both perfect, when asthere is an indiſſoluble knot betwéene them both, for where ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they are not both preſent they are both abſent: becauſe the one cannot</q>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:12040:16"/>
                  <q>ſerued luſt. They are altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of a reward who haue endured no trauiale to deſerue it, for it is fit that thoſe that haue ſought beſt ſhould haue the glory of the victorie. <bibl>Iſydore.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Chaſtitie is an ornament of noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, an exaltation of inferior perſons, the nobilitie of the ignoble, the beautie of the deformed, the ioy of mourners, an encreaſe of all comlineſſe, an ornament of religion, a leſſener of others offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, a multiplier of deſerts, and a friend of all creatures which God hath made. <bibl>Cyprian.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Six things conſerue chaſtitie vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, to wit: Sabrietie, labour, roughneſſe of apparrell reſtraint of the ſences, little talke vitered honeſtly, ſhunning of oportunitie both of the perſon, time, and place. <bibl>Caſſiodorus.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is a greater matter to roote vp the fuell of luſt in our owne nature, then to expell vncleane ſpirites out of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <bibl>Beda.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is an eaſier matter to reſtraine the vnknowne pleaſure of the fleſh, then once hauing tried it, to forgoe it. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:12040:16"/>Chaſtitie is a vertue, not onely brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the aſſaults of luſt, but alſo ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the occaſions. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Correction.</head>
                  <q>TO bridle by the raine of reaſon, an in-bred error, or cauſed by cuſtome, may rightly be termed Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We neuer ought to thide others for their offences, vnleſſe out owne conſcience doe firſt inwardly tell vs, that it procéedeth from loue, and not of hatred, ambition or vaine glory. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Loue hartely and then ſpeake what thou wilt. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The Phiſitian vnto the raging fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke man is troubleſome, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſéemeth troubleſome in nurtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his ſonne, the one by binding, the other by beating, but both by louing: But if either Parent or Phiſition by neglect ſhould ſuffer either of both to periſh, it might be more rightly termed exactlie then loue <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Publike offences ought to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likly</q>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:12040:17"/>
                  <q>forth into the maine Deean, and then being vnable to paſſe further, are forced to retire the ſame way they come euen ſo they began in ignorance, and ended in ignorance. <bibl>Chryſoſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Curioſitie is the ſearching out of ſuper flnous matters which nothing belong vnto a man <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We ought not to pry into thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets which God would not haue knowne: but thoſe things which he hath reuealed are not to be neglected, leaſt in the former we be fonnd ouer curious, and in the later damnably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull. <bibl>Proſper.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Conuerſation.</head>
                  <q>HOly conuerſation c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>onfoundeth a mans enemie, edifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th a mans neighbour, and glorifieth God. <bibl>Iſydo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is an excellent thing to liue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly iuſtly, and holyly amongſt the wirked and vngodly. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is no great praiſe worthy matter to be good amongſt the good, but to be good amongſt the wicked: for as it is at
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12040:17"/> greater offence not to be good with the good, ſo is it moſt worthy a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d like a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant champion, to be good amongſt the bad. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The Miniſters of Chriſt ſo ought to behaue themſelues, that their inwards liues may be anſwerable to their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward conuerſation. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Pythagora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> when a certaine man in his hearing ſaid, that he had rather be conuerſant with women then with Philoſophers, anſwered, ſo had Swins rather wallow in the mire then in the cleare water. <bibl>Val. Max.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>So behaue thy ſelfe towards thy inferiour, as thou wouldeſt haue thy ſuperiour to behaue himſelfe towards thée. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12040:18"/>
               <head>D.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Diſcipline.</head>
                  <q>HE that but a little while, for ſhams refuſeth diſcipline, ſhall euer after remaine in the ſhame of fooliſhneſſe. <bibl>Pythagoras.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Humilitie is the beginning of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, whereof (there being many do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments,) theſe three are moſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to be regarded of the learner. Firſt that he eſtéeme not baſely of any mans writings or ſcience. Secondly that he be not aſhamed to learne of any: Thirdly when he hath gotten knowledge, that he condemne not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Oh how ſetled diſcipline cauſeth euery ſtate both of the body and alſo of the minde to be. It ſubiecteth the neck, ſetleth the eye liddes, ordereth the countenance, ruleth the eyes, bridleth laughter, moderateth the tongue, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth the throate, aſſwageth anger,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12040:18"/> paſſifieth rage. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We ought carefully to beware that he which ſéeketh knowledge, deſpiſe not diſcipline. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Education &amp; diſcipline forme man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and euery one is wiſe in that which he hath learned.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Diſcord and Diſſention.</head>
                  <q>BY concord and diſagréement ſmall things become great, but by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and diſagréement great things vaniſh and become weake.</q>
                  <q>Whoſoeuer out wardly aſſlicteth his body, but abhorreth concord, praiſeth God outwardly, but hateth him in his heart. <bibl>Hierome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>As nothing is more acceptable vnto God then loue, ſo nothing is more wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come then chiding and brawling vnto the deuill: whoſoeuer therefore by ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſcoulding drineth his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour out of charitie, ſerueth the deuill and not God. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Contentions men can offer no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12040:19"/> ſacrifice vnto God, as long as they are out of loue and charitie with their neighbours. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Diſcord is the falling out of ſome who before were tied together with the bond of loue. Concord is an agréement of minds in honeſt &amp; vpright manner: but he that ſoweth ſtrife, or hatcheth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is a ſeditious perſon: the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of diſcord is, to claime that proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie his owne, which was common vnto others: nothing is more vnbeſéeming, then to fall out with thoſe with whom thou haſt liued familiarly. Flie conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions eſpecially, for to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>riue with thine equall is doubtfull, to contend with thy ſuperiour is madneſſe, to fall out with thy inferiour is baſeneſſe, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to enter the liſtes with one that is light headed, for he hurteth him that is abſent which ſtriueth with a drunkard. <bibl>Iſydore.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:12040:19"/>
                  <head>Delight and pleaſure.</head>
                  <q>THey ſooneſt féele afflictions, who haue béene before acquainted with continuall delights. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Thoſe moſt often drawe vexations from the fleſh, who are moſt delighted with the pleaſutes of the fleſh. <bibl>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that in his youth giueth himſelfe vnto delights and pleaſures, in old age ſhall vndergoe many ſorrowes. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Pleaſure and delight beate a man and ſo leaue him, wound a man and then giue him the ſlip, make him wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and then leaue him in miſerie. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Corporall delights are greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired before they be had, and when they are had they preſently make a man weary thereof: but contrarily ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall delights, when a man hath them not, are loathed: but being had are more and more deſired: in the formet the appelite begetteth fulneſſe, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12040:20"/> diſdaine: but in the latter the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite begetteth fulneſſe, and fulneſſe appetite: For ſpirituall delights doe increaſe the deſire thereof in the minde euen when they doe alſo fill. <bibl>Gregoric.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Deſperation.</head>
                  <q>DEſperation is an aſſured death, and the murtheret of the ſoule. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>To commit any ſinne is death vnto the ſoule: but to diſpaire throweth it quite into hell. <bibl>Iſydore.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Repentance is appointed as an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen againſt diſpaire: and the day of death is vncertaine, to the ende we ſhould not increaſe our ſinnes. <bibl>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Let no man diſpaire: <hi>Iudas</hi> periſhed not ſo much for his offence, as becauſe he deſpaired of pardon. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The firſt way to ſaluation, is to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the offence, the ſecond not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of pardon. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Deſperation ſhutteth heauen gates
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12040:20"/> againſt vs: hope openeth, and faith maketh a broad entrance. <bibl>Iſydore.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>In mans life his end is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected and not his beginning, for God regardeth not what manner men we line, but what we dye. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Oh <hi>Iudas</hi> more wicked then all men, whoe by repentance turned vnto God, but by deſperation yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himſelfe vnto the deuill. <bibl>Leo Papa.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He relyeth vpon worldly vertue, that diſpaireth of Gods ayde and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Detraction.</head>
                  <q>OVr patience is tryed by detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Nothing is more eaſte then for one that is idle and ſlouthfull to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from other mens labours. <bibl>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Detract not from any mans good deſeruings: and if be ſo thou deſire to ſéeme praiſe worthy by an other</q>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:12040:21"/>
                  <head>Deuill.</head>
                  <q>THere is a certaine wicked and craftie ſpirit, an enemy vnto man, and an hater of iuſtice. This ſpirit (the Deuill) not fortune, layeth trappes for all men, and thoſe that knowe not God he hindereth with error, he outt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmeth with fooliſhneſſe, he compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with darkneſſe that they may not come vnto the knowledge of God, in whome alone wiſdome and euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life conſiſteth: but thoſe that know God, thoſe he aſſaulteth by craft and ſubtiltie, that he may hinder them by luſt or incontinencie, or if they be (as all men are) ſtained with ſinne, he threateneth them with death, and if craſt ſaile, he aſſayeth to quell them by force. For they which attribute vnto fortune the power to beſtowe good and euill, are too credulous vnto worldly and vaine opinions. <bibl>Lactantius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The Deuill enuieth man-kinde, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to ſubiect that vnto himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12040:21"/> he foreſawe that man would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come God. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is the Deuils part to ſuggeſt euill, it is ours not to conſent. As often as we reſiſt them, ſo often we ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, we honour God who viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that we ſhould ſight: helpeth, that we may ouercome: ſtrengthneth vs, that we quaile not. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The Deuill is a craſtie enemie, whoſe firſt ſuggeſtion if we reſiſt not, he poſſeſſeth wholye before we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares. <bibl>Iſydore.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The Deuill when he intendeth to deceiue any man, firſt endeuoureth to know his nature, and thereby gath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto what ſinne he is moſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>By how much the Deuill per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the end of the worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to approache nearer, by ſo much the more he perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth, deſiring that he may bring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vnto hell, wherevnto he knoweth himſelf to be foorthwith condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:12040:22"/>
               <div type="section">
                  <q>reſt him whom thou enuieſt: <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Whiles the elect profit in goodneſſe, the reprobates are mooued vnto ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame rage, and doe perſecute thoſe growing good things, which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues would not imitate. <bibl>Nazianze.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>I am a man, but I know not how to ſhun the enuie of worldly things, it is eaſier for a poore man to flye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, then for a riche man to anoyde enuie. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Thou canſt no wayes more gaule and ſret the enuious man, then by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſernant vnto vertue and good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Vnderſtand what Enuie is: It is a repining at anothers good. And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand alſo this, that no vertuous man enuieth any man. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The enuious man is angry cloſely, but enemy like. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:12040:22"/>
                  <head>Exerciſe.</head>
                  <q>EXerciſe is a continuall vſe and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Mans life may ſitly be compared vnto Yron: for Yron if it be vſed, is worne by little and little: but if it be not vſed, it will be preſently conſumed with ruſt: euen ſo by exerciſe, a man at length is ſpent: but if thou exerciſe nothing, ſloath and idleneſſe will more conſume thée then continuall exerciſe. <bibl>Aulus Gell.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>All arts, and all maner crafts, by day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe and practiſe doe profit, which ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is true in ſmall matters, how much more carefully ought it to be vſed in great and waightie matters. <bibl>Vegetius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>By diligence the hardneſſe of any worke is eaſed: euen ſo prudence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſtice is little worth: but iuſtice without purdence is of much value: and likewiſe knowledge with practiſe is little worth: but ſkill and practiſe conioyned are very auaileable. <bibl>Boetius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:12040:23"/>Experience prooueth, that all artes without practiſe are hardly kept: and euen as the armes by long intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from their buſineſſe become vnfit and vnapt, ſo likewiſe witte if it be not vſed, decayeth. <bibl>Caſſiod.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Reading is a way to inſtruction, but conference being conioyned profiteth more: for conſerence canſeth docibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie more then reading dooth, becauſe by conference all doubts are reſolued, and often by queſtioning the hidden veritie appeareth, which otherwiſe had béene vureuealed. <bibl>Iſydore.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Excuſe.</head>
                  <q>THe multitude of companions, cauſeth not the fault to be alow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able or vnpuniſhable. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He offendeth twiſe, who ſéeketh to excuſe a bad turne by defending it. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Whatſoeuer company thou fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenteſt, beware that thou intermedle not much with others conuerſation,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12040:23"/> and if it be ſo that any amiſſe be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, ſéeke rather to excuſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then to accuſe the dooer. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A mans owne conſcience is an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured excuſe, howſoeuer he be cenſured by others. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Euery man can frame ſome excuſe; the proud man would ſéeme conſtant: the prodigall, liberall: the couetous man a good huſband, the raſh and haſty would be thought valtant: the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throate miſer, a ſparer: the ſluggiſh, quiet: and the fearefull wretch would ſéeme wary. <bibl>Proſper.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Lay aſide excuſes, no man ſinneth vn willingly, for all ſinne is voluatarie. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A childe is excuſed by his age, a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by her fire, a ſtranger by libertie, an houſhold body by familiaritie, and a friend is as ones ſelfe. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Giue not hard ſentence againſt thy neighbour, but rather excuſe him. If thou cannot excuſe the fact, yet excuſe the intention, ſuppoſe ignorance to be the cauſe of the offence, ſuppoſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hay,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12040:24"/> ſuppoſe ouer ſight. But if the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintle of the matter will not admit excuſe, yet perſwade thy ſelfe, and ſay vnto thy ſelfe thus: The temptation was great, and forcible, and I my ſelfe might haue béene ouercome by the like, if it had happened vnto me. <bibl>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>If a man commit an eſcape or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, his intention and meaning being good, God forbid that it ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected vnto him, becauſe he did euill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Thoſe are not fault worthy, who commit ſmall offences, that greater may be anoyded: for it is not loſſe to looſe a little, if by the loſſe thereof a great deale may be ſaned. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It oftentimes happeneth that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt wicked men cannot defend thoſe faults whereof they are accuſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come impudent, and ſo waxe proud in their owne defence, and ſéeking to find out faults in him who accuſeth, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thinke themſelues blameleſſe: and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be ſo they cannot finde out ought
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12040:24"/> which they may iuſtly blam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, then they finde hoales where no hoales are, that they may haue wherewith to cloake their owne vices. <bibl>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Although things are true, yet ought they not to be beléened without ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient proofe, or confeſſion of the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents themſelues: for not he that is accuſed, but he that is conuicted, is guiltie. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>This is a great fault in many men, that when they ſhould repent them of their faultes, they frame excuſes, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>end more by drawing defences for their faults from thence, whenes repentance ought to procéede. <bibl>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiod.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:12040:25"/>
                  <head>Example.</head>
                  <q>HE that liueth well ſecretly, and giueth no example vnto other mens, procéedings may be compared vnto a coale which, burneth inwardly, but outwardly ſéemeth to be dead. But he who leadeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n vpright life both pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately and publickly may be compared vnto a Lampe, which burneth it ſelfe and giueth light alſo vnto others. <bibl>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is a thing ingraffed by nature, that a ſhamefaſt man ſhould loue him that is chaſte, a wiſe man him that is diſcréete, a pittifull man him that is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall: and that all men ſhould loue their owne vertues in other men alſo. Oftentimes the very countenance of an honeſt man is a chaſtiſement vnto the vniuſt, and a ioy vnto the vpright. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>There are many men who are more readily drawne vnto the loue of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and heauenly things, by example,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12040:25"/> then by preaching. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>I eſtéeme no counſail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> better, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> (if thou deſire to inſtruct thy brother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thoſe things which ought to be done) that thou ſtirre him vp vnto better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, not perſwading him by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> but by déede and actions. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>No man is more hurtfull in the Church, then he who liuing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, cloaketh his actions with the name of holineſſe, or by reaſon of his order or degrée. For no man preſuming to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue him becauſe of his miniſtery, his faults are more hurtfull by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto others, becauſe others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the offender, by reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and thinke that lawfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> by themſelues, which their gho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth before them. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Euery one who being a ruler, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wickedly and vniuſly in the ſight of thoſe ouer whom he ruleth, as much as in him lyeth, deſtroyeth them and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it may ſo fall out that ſome not imitating him eſcape, yet all as for him, periſh.</q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:12040:26"/>The later day is a Scholler vnto the former: A wiſe man by an others fault will indeuour to amende his owne. It is good to tread our prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſors ſteppes, if they haue gone well before vs. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Euery good Chriſtian, ought to take example of good life at Chriſt and his actions. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>F.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Flattery.</head>
                  <q>WHoſoeuer flattereth euill liuers, layeth a pillow vnder the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ds head: inſomuch that he who ought to be reprehended for his ſault, being incouraged therein becommeth worſe and worſe. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>As the ſcoape of the Orator is by loue to perſwade, and of the Phiſitian by medicines to cure: Euen ſo the ſlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer intendeth by his faire wordes nought but to deceiue. <bibl>Chryſoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:12040:26"/>Euery flatterer is an enemie vnto vertue, and dooth as it were ſtrike a naile into his eye with whom be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth: and ought by ſo much the more diligently to be looked vnto, by how much the more he ſéemeth to loue. <bibl>Chryſoſtome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Nothing ſo much corrupteth mens mindes as flatterie: for his tongue cutteth more kéene then the weapons of our perſecutors. <bibl>Hierom.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Deceiuable flattery is a moſt creuen thing. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The tongues of flatterers binde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in their vices: for it delighteth a man to doe thoſe things, for which he feareth not the reprehender, but alſo looketh to be praiſed for performing them. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>When we are paſſing vnto our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly country, we ought not to giue eare vnto the Syrenian ſongs of flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers. <bibl>Hierom.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Flattery is the very nurſe of ſinne, which is accuſtomed to adminiſter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto thoſe who doe amiſſe, as eyls yéeldeth liquor vnto the flame. <bibl>Beda.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:12040:27"/>
                  <q>We are then faithfull, when we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme in déede that which we promiſe in wordes. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Infidelitie is by nature like vnto a ſandy barren ground which is alwaies fruitleſſe be it neuer ſo well watered. <bibl>Chryſoſtome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>That man hath all in himſelfe, which hath himſelfe: but no man hath himſelfe which hath not God, and he hath God who beléeueth in him, and acknowledgeth him to be the author of his ſaluation. <bibl>Caſſiod.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that looſeth his faith hath nothing elſe for to looſe. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Faith is an aſſured conceiuing of the trueth without any knowledge of the cauſe thereof. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>As to be alwayes learning argueth that a man is neuer perfect, euen ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to ſéeke for witneſſes argueth that a man vnwilling to beléeue. <bibl>Chryſoſtome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>As the hard ſtones being wrought in a worke are permanent, ſo the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles albeit they are hardly brought
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12040:27"/> vnto beléefe, yet once beléeuing they perſeuere therein. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Doe not vnderſtand that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt beléeue, but beléeue that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt vnderſtand: for vnderſtanding is the reward of faith. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Faith is more wealthy then all wordly riches, more ſtrong then all humaine ſtrength, more wholeſome then all earthly Phiſick.</q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>G.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Greeſe.</head>
                  <q>THere is no griefe which by tract of time is not leſſened and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A good courage in extreame gréefe is a remedie therof. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>No man can gréeue long and much withall: for ſo hath louing nature diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that our griefe might be eyther ſhort or tollerable, and this is a comfort in ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reame anguiſhes, that eyther they will endour liues or we ouercome them. <bibl>Senaca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:12040:28"/>Griefe if thou yéelde vnto it will breake t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y heart: but if thou reſiſt it it will be ouercome of thée.</q>
                  <q>He more eaſilie vndergoeth griefe, who is accuſtomed therevnto, then he that hath ſeldome taſted thereof. <bibl>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Euery man is by ſo much the more perfect, by how much he dooth more throughly conceiue anothers griefe. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A due conſideration of the cauſe thereof, dooth mittigate the ſharpneſſe of the griefe.</q>
                  <q>He that is endued with fortitude, deſpiſeth and ſetteth light both by griefe and death it ſelfe. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We may hardly beléeue a gréeued minde: for griefe will compell the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent ſometimes to frame a lye. <bibl>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He is riche, who is able to beare with an vpright minde whatſoeuer euilles or vexations doe happen. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We haue greater cauſe to gréeue
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12040:28"/> when ones owne deſert cauſed the ſame, then when we are puniſhed wrongfully; for we ought rather to ioy, then gréeue, when we ſuffer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Inward griefe ſooner bringeth a man vnto the graue, then outward ſorrow which commeth not them the heart. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>If thou ſuffer affliction, if wante, and neceſſitie, if perſecution, if ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and vniuſt defamations, or what ſoeuer els, take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> patiently and gréeue not, and Gods holy ſpirit ſhall mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto thée ſufficient ſtrength to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe all miſeries and calamities. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Be ready to adminiſter comfort vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the gréeued ſoule, and adde not griefe vnto griefe.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:12040:29"/>
                  <head>Guile and Deceit.</head>
                  <q>POyſons that they may deceiue, are enuolued in Dunnie, and vices de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue not but vnder the ſhew and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of vertues. <bibl>Ambroſius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Many men liue plainely and proſper in all things, and many deale alwayes ſubtiltie and yet are alwayes behinde hand. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Many men liue plainely and proſper in all things, and many deale alwayes ſubſtillie and yet are alwayes behinde hand. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A man may more eaſily ſhunne the dangers of a profeſſed ſhe, then of a ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned friend, becauſe for the one he will be alwayes armed, but for the other he is vnprouided. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A guilefull enemie endeuoureth to make a ſhewe of loue: and yet deſireth to wound. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is deceit when one thing is done, and another made ſhew to be intended. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He is craſtie who imitateth vertue by guile and deceit.</q>
                  <q>There are many who being endued with ſharpe wittes, abuſe their good
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12040:29"/> guiſts by conuirting them vnto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite and guilefull dealings. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He dealeth not deceitfully in Gods worke, who when he giueth himſelfe vnto good ſtudies, diſireth not humane praiſes nor worldly preſerments.</q>
                  <q>He dealeth deceitfully who by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing the truth, ſéeketh either his owne commoditie, or anothers diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie. <bibl>Aulus Gel.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Words are appointed not that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men ſhould deceiue one another, but that thereby one man might open his thoughts vnto another: wherefore to vſe words to deceiue and not to that end that they were appointed, is a great ſinne. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Perſidiouſnes is an hidden &amp; decein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able euil, whoſe moſt effectuall powers, are to deceiue and ſlatter. <bibl>Val. Max.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He who deceiueth his friend that repoſeth his truſt in him, is more to be deteſted then he that deceiueth him that repoſed no confidence in him.</q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:12040:30"/>
               <head>H.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Hereſie.</head>
                  <q>HE is an Heretique, who for deſire of any temporall commoditie, and eſpecially of glory and renowne, broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth new opinions. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He is an Heretique who obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defendeth an error, after the trueth is manifeſted.</q>
                  <q>Let Heretiques diſpute wholy out of the Scriptures, and not inſiſt vpon ſuch points as the Pagans and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels doe, and their opinions will eaſily be ouerthrowne. <bibl>Tertullian.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Heretiques bring in a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Apocryſall bookes and baſſard writings, that they may amaze the vndiſcréete, and ſuch as are ignorant in Gods booke. <bibl>Ireneus.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Heretiques ſearing to be ouercome by the truth, and thereby compelled to ſhake hands with vs, fall a rayling, or els ſtoppe their cares, that they may
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12040:30"/> not heare, or their eyes that they may not ſée the trueth, and ſo be conuerted. <bibl>Lactantius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Heretiques reſpect not ſo much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt life, ciuill conuerſation, and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull pittie towards the diſtreſſed, as to be praiſed and boaſted, if be ſo they may but ſéeme to ouercome by ſyllogiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, ſallacies, and falſe arguments. <bibl>Sozome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Rotten fleſh is to be eaten away, and ſcabbie ſheepe to be ſeperated from the ſhéepfould, leaſt the whole man and the whole flock be deſtroyed, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. <hi>Arrius</hi> was but one ſparke in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> but becauſe he had not béene at the firſt ſuppreſſed, the whole citie, and country was ſet on fire and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>As thoſe that haue a wicked opinion, albeit their conuerſation be outwardly good, are to be taken héede of, euen ſo are they alſo to be taken héed off, who are of ſound opinion, and yet liue wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly. <bibl>Chryſoſtome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Many ſéeking by comtemplation to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12040:31"/> obteine more then they are able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, runne into peruerſe errors: and whiles they refuſe with humilitie to be the Schollers of truth, they become maiſters of errors. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Humilitie.</head>
                  <q>EVen as a Trée to the end it may growe an bright, ought to haue good roote downeward: ſo whoſoeuer hath not his minde fixed vpon humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is exalted vnto his owne ruine. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Thy country is on high, and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie the waye therevnto, wherefore then if thou deſireſt to come vnto thy country dooſt thou leaue the way which leadeth therevnto. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Humilitie oftentimes boweth that which neyther force, nor might could cauſe to bend. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>By humilitie all our déedes are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Whoſoeuer death not héere on earth
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12040:31"/> himſelfe, ſhall hardly be partaker of the glory in heauen. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Humilitie is a glorious thing, and pride it ſelfe deſireth to be cloaked with the name thereof, leaſt it growe into contempt. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is true humilitie for one to eſtéeme baſely of ones owne ſelfe, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend good partes in another without either malice or ranckor. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Whoſoeuer thinketh to be truely vertuous without humility, dooth as he who gathereth duſte vpon an heape, and placeth it in the winde, which is no ſooner downe but it is carried away. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that is humble in minde, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéemeth of others more then himſelfe, deſireth not ſuperioritie: and dignitie ſlieth from him that proſecuteſh it, but proſeeuteth him that flyeth from it. <bibl>Chryſoſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>To be truly humbled, is a ſure ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of grace.</q>
                  <q>Humilitie is the way vnto humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, euen as patience is the way vnto
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12040:32"/> peace, or reading vnto knowledge, therefore if thou deſire to be humble walke in the way therevnto, for he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that is truly humble ſpareth his owne ſoule, who becauſe he would not be thought to be that which he was not, as much as he can deſireth not to be knowne to be that which he is. <bibl>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Humilitie eſpecially conſiſteth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that we ſubiect all our actions vnto Gods will. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Ignorance.</head>
                  <q>IGnorance of God, for the moſt part is the mother of diſpaire. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Many things are vnknowne, which ought to be knowne, which happeneth either by careleſneſſe to know, or ſloath to learne, or ſhame to enquire, and this ignorance is intollerable. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is as great an offence is be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in that which one ought to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12040:32"/> knowe, as it is to doe ſome things that ought not to be done. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that ſéeth the light knoweth how to iudge of darkneſſe, for he that is ignorant of the light, approoueth darkneſſe for light. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>They flatter themſelues vnto their owne condemnation, who that they might haue the more libertie to ſinne, are willingly ignorant. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that is moſt expert, wiſe, or wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, may iuſtly confeſſe that he is a ſcholler, yea altogether ignorant in ſome things. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>When as we know our owne ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, we will the more willingly be are others burthens. God neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh him who trulie knoweth his owne ſinnes. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Knowledge is two wayes neceſſary vnto ſaluation, to wit, knowledge of God &amp; of thy ſelfe: becauſe as by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy ſelfe thou learneſt to feare God, and by knowledge of God to loue God likewiſe: Euen ſo contrarily ignorance of thy ſelfe engendreth pride,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12040:33"/> and by ignorance of God thou falleſt into deſperation. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is better to be ignorant then to erre, and faithfull ignorance is better then rath knowledge. <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Infirmitie.</head>
                  <q>IN all diſeaſes there are three eſpeaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all gréeſes, to wit, feare of death, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily paine, and the intermiſſion of pleaſure. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Many men liue as they luſt, and yet are alwayes inſtie: and many neuer ſtray from <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> rules, and yet are alwayes ſickly. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Health is more welcome vnto thoſe that haue béene gréeuouſly ſicke, then vnto thoſe that neuer knew what ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe meant. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>No man is without ſome infirmitie, therefore beare with another mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, as thou wouldeſt another man ſhould beare with thine. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Laugh no man to ſcorne in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, leaſt another man doe the like
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12040:33"/> by thée alſo. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Iuſtice.</head>
                  <q>EVen as a Lanſhorne in the night giueth light, but in the day time the light thereof is not diſcerned, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo mans inſtice being compared with Gods inſtice, is altogether iniuſtice. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Iuſtice rather ſéeketh others com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie then ones owne, preferring the common good before a mans owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate gaine. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>All other vertues are contained vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of iuſtice alone. <bibl>Hierom.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is iuſtice to loue men for iuſtice ſake, and not to thinke ſcorne of iuſtice for the perſons ſakes. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Iuſtice is the libertie of the minds giuing vnto euery one his proper dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, to wit, reuerence vnto ones bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter agréement with ones equall, diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline vnto ones inferior, obedience to God, holineſſe vnto ones ſelfe, patience vnto ones enemie, and pittie vnto the diſſreſſed poore. <bibl>Anſelme.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:12040:34"/>Iuſtice reſpecteth neither father nor mother, but the truth onely: it accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth no mans perſon, it imitateth God. <bibl>Caſſiod.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>There is no greater iniuſtice then theirs, who when they moſt eſpecially deceiue, yet ſo handle the matter that they would ſéeme to be honeſt men. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A iuſt man will neuer thinke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe iuſt inough, but alwayes hung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and thirſteth thereafter: inſomuch that if he ſhould liue neuer ſo long, yet would he alwayes couet to be more iuſt. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The iuſtice of the King, is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects quiet, the defence of the country, the fréedome of the common people, the care of the diſtreſſed, the ioy of all men, the temperateneſſe of the ayre, the caime of the Seas, the fertilitie of the land, the comfort of the poore, the heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of ſonnes, and vnto himſelfe the hope of eternall happineſſe. <bibl>Cyprian.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Iuſtice giueth vnto euery one his owne: giue therefore vnto thrée that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12040:34"/> which belongeth vnto them: to wit, vnto the Prelate reuerence and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, the one whereof commeth from the heart, the other belongeth vnto the body: giue vnto thy equall counſaile to inſtrua his ignorance, and ayde to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour his infirmitie: giue vnto thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour admonition, that he may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, and correction that he proceede not in ſtnning.</q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>K.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Knowledge or Wiſdome.</head>
                  <q>HE moſt eſpeacially defireth to know God, who for the deſire that he hath vnto vertue, would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ignorant in worldly matters. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>They can neuer attaine true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, who deceiue themſelues with their owne vaine fooliſhneſſe <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The thieſeſt wiſedome is an vpright life, and iuſt hart to God-ward, wherby the pure with the pure, and the godly
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12040:35"/> with the godly are conioyned. <bibl>Nazi.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Idleneſſe is the mother of fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and labour of knowledge, the trauaile of knowledge is thréeſould; to wit, the labour of diſcipline, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and doctrine: in childhood diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, in youth exerciſe, and in olde age doctrine: in childhood to learne that that is vnknowne, in youth to practiſe that which in their childhood was lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and in olde age to inſtruct others therein. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Knowledge cannot be taken away by violence, nor corrupted by age, it is decreaſed by diſuſe, and enlarged by practiſe. <bibl>Caſſiod.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Knowledge ought to be greatly eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, for no man can faithfully ſéeke that whereof he is ignorant, and an vnknowne euill is neither feared, nor can be preuented. <bibl>Chryſoſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>There are ſome who deſire to know, to that end only that they may know, &amp; that is meare curioſitie: ſome likewiſe are deſirous of knowledge that they may ſel it, to wit, for money, for honors,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12040:35"/> and that is diſhoneſt gaine: and ſome there are that deſire to know that they may be knowne, and that is idle vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and ſome there are who are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of knowledge, that they may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, &amp; it is charitie: and ſome alſo are deſirous to know, that they may profit thereby, and it is wiſdome. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A wiſe man will admire nothing when once it is come to paſſe, nor yet iudge any thing impoſſible before it be effected. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>No man can liue well, nor yet in a meane, who careth not for wiſdom. <bibl>Sen.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>To know althings except God, and to be ignorant of God, is to know ney<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God nor any thing els. For he that is ignorant of God, is ignorant of his ſaluation, and he who is ignorant of his ſaluation, all his knowledge tendeth vnto his greater condemnation. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>To ſay that a man knoweth that wherein he is ignorant, is ouer raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and to ſay that he knoweth not that which he dooth knowe is ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:12040:36"/>A man ought to know that he is of himſelfe nothing, but what he is, he is of God, and for God. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Nothing more encourageth our hope to attaine knowledge, then the conſideration of this one thing, to wit, that thoſe who in times paſſed haue béene very ignorant and vnlearned are now become for their iudgement and knowledge admirable. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Vnto a wiſe man and one that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with knowledge, all places are alike, he ſuppoſeth himſelfe to be no where a ſtranger, but euery place is vnto him as the place of his education. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that is in loue with himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a foole, ſhall neuer become wiſe, neither ſhall he become that which he would be, vnleſſe he deſpiſe that that he is. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>In learning the wiſeman findeth that whereby he may be made more wiſe, the warriour whereby he may be in minde incouraged, from thence the Prince learneth how to gouerne his
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12040:36"/> people quietly: and to be briefe, there is no ſtate of life which the excellent knowledge of letters may not better, and profit. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Nothing is more ſeruently loued then wiſdome, nothing more ſwéete in poſſeſſion: herehence it procéedeth that many deſire to become wiſe, but they faile in the attaining thereof: but all men may be iuſt if they perfectly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be iuſt. A man may loue wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome excéedingly, and yet faile to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it: but by how much more a man loueth iuſtice, by ſo much ſhall he be more iuſt.</q>
                  <q>Many hauing atteined vnto learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing end knowledge, vſe it not vnto Gods glory, but abuſe it vnto their owne praiſe, being puffed vp there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and ſo ſinne grieuouſly thereby from whence they ought to take good leſſons for the amendment of their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liues. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The wiſedome of the iuſt is, to faine nothing by oftentation, but to open the truth therof in words, to loue the truth
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12040:37"/> as it is truth, and to hate falſhood: to doe good fréely, and rather to beare euils patiently then off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r any willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: to eſtéeme reproache for the trueth ſake, gaine; but this ſimplicitie of the iuſt is derided of the world, becauſe they eſtéeme the puritie of vertue foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>L.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Learning.</head>
                  <q>EArthly proſperitie comforteth thè body, but the tongue of the learned, preaching the glad tidings of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, bringeth farre more comfort vnto the ſoule.</q>
                  <q>He that reprooueth all men by lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a life conformable vnto his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, ſufficiently declareth himſelfe to be learned: neyther is young age in a Doctor to be deſpiſed whom both his life and indgement doe commend. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>As it is a wiſe part to gather vine
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12040:37"/> branches in an hedge, and cluſters of grapes among thornes warely, leaſt that whiles thou ſéekeſt the profitte thereof, thou pricke thy fingers: euen ſo great care ought to be had, that thou imitate not him dooing euill, whome thou haſt heard ſpeake good things. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A mans life ought more to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded then his learning: for a good life without learning is commendable, but learning without a good life lacketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is as godly an act to inſtruct the minde with wiſedome, as it is to giue ſuſtenance vnto the body when it lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>In reading, not the wordes but the trueth is to be regarded: for often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the plaine trueth, and craftie falſhood are commixt, whereby ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple men are oftentimes intrapped, and ſwéete wordes make fooles faine: for the loue of worldlye ſkill dooth nought els but puffe a man with vaine
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12040:38"/> praiſes: and looke by how much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a mans ſtudies haue béene, by ſo much the more dooth it cauſe a man to ſwell with diſdaine. <bibl>Iſydore.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The ſinner hath his mouth ſhut, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe be that hath not taught himſelfe cannot inſtruct another. <bibl>Origen.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Little woorth is learning vnleſſe it be approoued by induſtry, ſtudy, labour and diligence. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The noble poſſeſſion of learning, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deuided amongſt many is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and being deuided into parts ſéeleth not any leſſoning at all, but wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth dayly ſo much the more durable olde, by how much the more it hath béene made common. <bibl>P. Bleſen.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>By other mens actions a man ought to learne what a man ought to doe himſelfe. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is more auaileable to heare one teach, then to ſtudie vpon the booke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thereby a more déepe impreſſion is made in the minde. <bibl>Val. Max.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:12040:38"/>
                  <head>Liberalitie.</head>
                  <q>IT ſkilleth of what minde and not of what ſtate he be that giueth, for it is not praiſe-worthy which is done of compulſion or brauerie. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Beware that thy liberalitie be not greater then thy abilitie, for in ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie there is alwayes a deſire of getting, eyther by huck or cruck, that thou mayeſt haue alwayes ſomewhat to giue: and moſt commonly thefts en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue ſuch liberalitie: for when by ſuch manner giuing thou beginneſt to be in neceſſitie, thou art forced to lay hands vpon other mens goods, and in ſo dooing thou precureſt greater hatred of thoſe from whome thou haſt wrongfully ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, then loue of thoſe to whome thou haſt vnwiſely giuen. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A good turne quickly done is twiſe done. He is leaſſe deceiued that is quickly denied, then he that is put in hope to obtaine by faire promiſes. If a man deny to giue vnto one whome he
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12040:39"/> hath alwaies béen accuſtomed to giue, he enforceth him to ſéeke it by crooked meanes. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Well anſwered <hi>Alexander</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine man vnto whome he had giuen a citie: for the man ſayd, that ſo great a gift became not his baſe fortune, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> replied, I eſtéeme not ſo much what it becommeth thée to receiue, as what it becommeth me to giue. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The hand neuer wanteth what to giue, if the heart be filled with good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will. <bibl>Hierom.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Liberalitie alwayes maketh haſt, and it is proper vnto a liberall man to doe that which he dooth quickly. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>For if a man profit an other, and yet protract time from day to day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he performe it, he looſeth two eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall things, to wit, both the time and the opinion of a friendly minde. <bibl>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Liberalitie is not defined by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vp of riches, but by the affection which thou haſt to giue. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:12040:39"/>It is more gréenous vnto a liberall man, not to haue beſtowed that which was behooue full, then to haue beſtowed that which was not behoouefull. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>M.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Miſerie.</head>
                  <q>HE knoweth well how to beare temporal miſeries, who knoweth how to reioyce with inward hope. <bibl>Gre.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Miſerie, is the aboundance of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, and wante of conſolation, when a man is many wayes cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, and yet caſed by no man. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>If we diligently conſider of the the matter, we ſhall finde that the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall miſerie of man-kinde is thrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fould, for we are eaſte to be ſeduced, weake to effect ought, and vnable to make reſiſtance. If we would iudge betwéene good and bad, we are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: if we aſſay to doe good we ſaint: if we deſire to reſiſt euill we are weake and eaſily ouercome. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:12040:40"/>A wiſe wretch is more a wretch, then a clowniſh miſer: for the former know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how to exagerate the cauſes of griefe, but the latter dooth not. <bibl>Boe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Sinners are to be adiudged by ſo much more miſerable, by how much the more often they are ſuffered to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede in their ſinnes vnchaſtened. <bibl>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Wherefore was I borne vnto la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and trauaile? my dayes are ſpent in confuſion. If he who was ſanctified in the wombe, ſpake ſuch wordes of himſelfe, what ſhall I wretched man ſay of my ſelfe, who was conceiued in ſinne, borne in ſinne, and yet vile wretch remaine in ſinne? woe vnto me poore wretch whom thou my mother haſt brought foorth euen the childe of vexation and ſorrow. Wherefore had I not dyed before I was brought foorth? Wherefore was I taken vp vpon the knées and nurſed? wherefore did I ſucke the dugges to prolong my life in miſerie? better had it béene for
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:12040:40"/> me, if dying in the wombe, I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer béene brought foorth, or being borne I had béene preſently brought vnto the graue, that thereby I might haue eſcaped the miſeries which now I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure. <bibl>Innocentias.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Man was made of duſt, dung, and aſhes, and which is worſer, of moſt fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſéede, conceined in the luſt of the fleſh, in the heate of luſt, in the ſtinking of luxurie, and which is worſt, of and in the ſpottes of ſinne, borne was man to labour, feare and griefe, and which is more miſerable, vnto death. He dooth wicked things, whereby he offendeth God, he offendeth his neighbour, and diſpleaſeth himſelfe. He committeth diſhoneſt things, whereby he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fileth himſelfe, ſtaineth his credit, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth his conſcience. He dooth vaine things, whereby he neglecteth things profitable and neceſſarie. His meate becommeth a fire which burneth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, and is neuer quenched: his foode a woorme which alwayes grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth without ceaſting, an heape of filthe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:12040:41"/> which alwayes ſtincketh moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Mercie and Pittie.</head>
                  <q>A Man ought to haue a great care with what minde he ſpareth for as there is a puniſhing pittie, ſo there is a ſparing pittie. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is a great comfort vnto the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſoule, when as a man being as it were wrapped in vices, and ſéeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe depriued of vertues, flyeth onely vnto the hope of Gods mercie. <bibl>Greg.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>God is mercifull &amp; of great pittie; God is mercifull vnto all men, and his mercies are aboue all his workes. Oh vile man dooſt thou heare of ſo great mercies and yet relyeſt vpon thine owne vertues and deſeruings. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>All men are found guiltie, both Iewes and Gentiles, and all haue néed of Gods mercie. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>When as mans helpe moſt faileth, then ought we moſt eſpecially to relye vpon Gods fauour and ſuccour. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:12040:41"/>Pittie conſiſteth in giuing almes, in forbearing wrongs, in remitting iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and in inſtructing the vnſkilfull.</q>
                  <q>Mercie is the helmet of ſaluation, the ornament of faith, the propitiation of ſinnes: this is it which prooueth the iuſt, ſtrengtheneth the godly, &amp; comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thoſe that ſerue God deuoutly.</q>
                  <q>It is a more mercifull déede to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and helpe the poore that want, then the rich that lack not: for he that giues vnto one that hath not néede thereof, dooth as it were powre water into a veſſell which runneth ouer before. <bibl>Caſſ.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Let not him that hath vnderſtanding be ſilent, neither let him which hath plenty with hold his hand from giuing: let him that hath oportunitie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tte meanes, not faile but make interceſſion with the rich for the poore, leaſt he incur the penalty of damnation of retaining their talent. <bibl>Raba.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Mercie is ſo great a vertue, that without it, other vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, although they be, cannot auaile: for although a man be faithfull, chaſſe, ſober, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:12040:42"/> endued with other worthy vertuas, yet if he be not mercifull, he ſhall not obtaine mercis. <bibl>Leo Papa.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>N.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Nature.</head>
                  <q>NAture is content with the leaſt and ſmalleſt things.</q>
                  <q>Nature dooth make many ſignes and tokens vnto vs that we might vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what ſhe meaneth: but we become deafe, not hearing what ſhée ſaith. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Education altereth nature, as by the example of the two Dogges pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding from one Dam at one litter, the one whereof being vſed vnto the pot, the other vnto hunting, before which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Hare and a potte of Pottage being placed, the one followed the Hare, and the other can preſently vnto the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage pot. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is good to breake thoſe that are of a ſtubborne nature whiles they be
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:12040:42"/> young, leaſt when they become elder they be too ſtrong to be ruled: as by the example of the twig, which when it is young may be bowed any waye, but being growne vnto ſome bigneſſe is not able to be bended. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>That which is bred in the bones will neuer out of the fleſh, neither is it poſſible, that man that is borne of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fleſh, ſhould be cleane without ſpot of ſinne. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>God and nature haue made no things in vaine, for all things ſerue vnto ſome purpoſe, but man wanteth knowledge to apply euery thing vnto his proper end. <bibl>Ariſtotle.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We ought to hould the ſame courſe that nature hath preſcribed vnto vs, not declining there from: all things are eaſie and plaine vnto thoſe which haue an inſight thereinto, but thoſe that reſiſt nature doe as it were ſtriue againſt the ſtreame. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Man is by nature wicked, naught, and corrdyt, neither can ſo much as a good thought procéede from vs, vnleſſe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:12040:43"/> our nature be ſeaſoned with the ſalte of Gods holy ſpirit, which is the true guide that leadeth vs vnto eternall bliſſe, which our owne nature cannot attaine vnto.</q>
                  <q>Nature is an vpright diſpenſor, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing vnto euery one that which is agréeable.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Negligence.</head>
                  <q>NEgligence is the ſlouth of the minde, whereby euery one is negligent in the performance of that wherevnto he ought to haue an eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all regarde. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>If ſometimes we be ſeduced to let ſlippe ſmall things without any reſpect therevnto, we will in time growe more bould to commit greater ouer-ſlippes without any care. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We are all of vs very circumſpect in ſmall matters, but very negligent in great and waighty affaires, and the occaſion hereof is becauſe we are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the true liſe. <bibl>Hiero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</bibl>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:12040:43"/> A great puniſhment hangeth ouer their heads, who doe the Lords worke negligently, as eſpecially ouer the heads of Preachers and Paſtors, who for lacke of ſpirituall foode ſuffer their flockes to periſh, and to become a pray vnto the deuill, whiles they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues neglecting their owne charge, giue themſelues vnto ſlouth and idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We ought not to doe our buſineſſe negligently, but with care, héedful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and warily: and eſpecially ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ought not to be idle, but well ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed, whether they be in their Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſight or not, knowing that the Lorde their ſpirituall Maiſter ſéeth at all times whether they be negligent or not. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Nobilitie.</head>
                  <q>THe chiefeſt libertie is to be with God, and not to ſerue ſinne: and the chiefeſt nobili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie with God is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in vertues. <bibl>Hierom.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:12040:44"/>I cannot greatly praiſe Nobilitie: for a good man ſéemeth vnto me noble: but he that is iniuſt although he be deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended of a better ſtocke then <hi>Iupiter</hi> himſelfe, ſéemeth vnto me baſe and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble. <bibl>Demoſthenes.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The Nobilitie of our kindred little auaileth, vnleſſe we our ſelues be good and noble: for by how much the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou art by birth, if thou excell not in vertues alſo, thou art by ſo much the more culpable and reproouable. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>O.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Obedience.</head>
                  <q>IT is better to obey God then man, and it is better to obey our maiſters then our fellow Schollers: and it is alſo better to obey thoſe that haue rule ouer vs, then ſtrangers: wherefore without doubt, not to obey thoſe whom moſt eſpecially we ought, is moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſtable. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:12040:44"/>Certainely he that ſheweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ready to obey before he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, deſerueth more thankes then he that obeyeth after commandement giuen. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We ought to obey, not with ſeruile feare, but with affectionate loue, not for feare of puniſhment, but for loue of iuſtice, and for right couſneſſe ſake. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Perfect obedience is ignorant of the lawe, neither is it reſtrained with bounds. Yea it dooth performe more willingly then is commanded of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Nothing is more vniuſt, then that a man ſhould deſire to be obeyed of his inferiours, who himſelfe will not yéelde obedience vnto his ſuperiours. <bibl>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>In obedience this is a generall rule to be obſerued, that by how much more difficult the matter is, by ſo much the more praiſe-worthy is obedience: and by how much more eaſie the matter is to be performed, by ſo much more
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:12040:45"/> great is the offence if it be not effected, then the matter deſerued praiſe if it had béene fulfilled. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Diſobedience procéedeth from the obſtinacie of a ſtubborne minde, not willing to obey him that iuſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>If (thy ſuperiour commanding the contrary) thou vſe any words at vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wates, it is an offence: but if thou ſpeake raſhly and willingly, the offence is by ſo much more the greater.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Obſtinacie.</head>
                  <q>THere are thrée ſortes of obſtinate men: the firſt is of thoſe who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit nothing by correction: the ſecond of thoſe who by correction are made worſe, and the thrid of thoſe who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe amendment, but do not according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: by correction <hi>Manaſles</hi> was made better: <hi>Naball</hi> by admonition became worſer: and <hi>Pharao</hi> by affliction was more hardened. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is méere obſtinacie, out of the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:12040:45"/> vnreaſonable and vncontrouled perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie of the minde, to refuſe to yéelde obedience vnto better things. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Then is our infelicitie conſummated, when as diſhoneſt things doe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delight, but alſo pleaſe, and hardly can there be any place for remedie, when as thoſe things which haue béene vices, are accoumpted vertues. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Order and degrees.</head>
                  <q>BY order things are conſerued, but by diſorder things come vnto ruine and confuſion.</q>
                  <q>Not our degrées and dignities make vs néereſt vnto God, but our loues eyther good or bad, doe conioyne vs vnto him, or ſeuer vs from him. <bibl>Collumb.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Euery man ought to acknowledge his owne order and degrée, and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what belongeth therevnto, and ſo to order &amp; gouerue his actions,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:12040:46"/> wordes, geſtures and manner of his habite, that it be agréeable vnto his degree, leaſt he heare this ſaide vnto him by God. <hi>Becauſe my name was blaſphemed among the Gentiles for your ſake, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>None ought to be admitted vnto holy functions, but thoſe whoſe integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of life hath béene formerly approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that ordereth his owne ſteppes rightly, giueth light alſo vnto others how they ought to walke.</q>
                  <q>Children ought not to be admitted vnto holy orders, leaſt they doe by ſo much. the ſooner fall and come vnto ruine, by how much the greater haſt they made to clime vnto promotion. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:12040:46"/>
               <head>P.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pouertie.</head>
                  <q>MIſerable is the ſtate of the poore man: if he begge he is aſhamed, if he begge not, he pineth with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and yet to begge neceſſitie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth him. He blameth God as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt, becauſe he hath not rightly (in his iudgment) deuided the wealth of the world: he accuſeth his neighbour of enuie, becauſe he yéeldeth him not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour: he frowneth, murmureth, and curſeth: where vpon the wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaid; <hi>It is better to die then to liue in want:</hi> and to be briefe, if thou be poore thy brother will forſake thée, and thy friends depart from thée. <bibl>Innocentius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The poore man that hath almoſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, yet being content poſſeſſeth all things, and on the contrary, the riche man which hath many things, yet wanting content, is as he that hath nothing.</q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:12040:47"/>The poore man cannot be happy in his owne minde, vnleſſe he haue ſéene thoſe that haue béene in proſperitie to haue ſuffered ſhipwrack: ioyfull po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie is an honeſt thing, but it cannot be pouertie, that is borne chéerefully, for he that taketh pouértie patiently is is a rich man: and not he that hath lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but he that deſireth much is a poore man. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Pouertie ought to be loued, if for nothing els, yet for this cauſe onely, becauſe thereby thou t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yeſt who are thy fréends, and who not. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Pouertie hath this one diſcommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, becauſe it wanteth wherewith to ſuccour thoſe that are in aduerſitie. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Pouertie is the beggerie of the mind, and not the want of wealth. <bibl>Gregory.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Thoſe that are poore in ſpirit, when they haue done any good thing, glorifie God: if any euill, they accuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is an hainous offence with a ſoornfull eye to deſpiſe our poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:12040:47"/> and diſdainfully to contemne them becauſe of their pouertie (who otherwiſe were our equalls) is no leſſe offenſiue. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The poore when all worldly meanes faile, yet then are they comforted in the Lord. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Preaching.</head>
                  <q>IT is a gréeuous offence, for thrée cauſes to conceale Gods wordes, to wit, either for feare, ſlouth or flattery. <bibl>Hierom.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Euery Sermon that edifieth not the hearers, is turned into their greater condemnation. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Euery doctor that peruerteth thoſe ſharpe ſayings of Scripture (whereby he ought to recall his bearers) vnto ſmooth ſayings, and ſpeaketh in ſuch manner that he correct not but deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his auditorie, corrupteth the pure iuice of Gods holy word, and mingleth it with his owne expoſition. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:12040:48"/>Many make long and tedious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, but without knowledge, and ſome againe ſpeake fewe wordes but much matter. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A man ought to be firſt himſelfe cleane, and ſo to cleanſe others: to be wiſe himſelfe, and then to teach others wiſedome: to be a light, and then to lighten others: to be ſanctified, and then to ſanctifie others. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A Preacher ought not to declare all things vnto the vnlearned which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe knoweth, becauſe the ignorant ought to be firſt inſtructed in more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie points, before they can be able to conceiue the more déepe and ſecret mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He gathereth large &amp; ample fruites of his preaching, which dooth before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe himſelfe in good workes: for the words want authoritie, if good déedes be wanting. <bibl>Nazianzene.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>If thou neglect to fulfill that which thy ſelfe teacheſt, thou ſoweſt thy ſelfe, and others gather in the harueſt. <bibl>Ide.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A Preacher ought to haue an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:12040:48"/> regarde vnto the time and place, and capacitie of his auditors, for one worde well and fitly placed, edifieth more then many vnaduiſedly offered. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>As the fleſh waxeth ſtrong by mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and delights, euen ſo the ſpirit is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with Gods word.</q>
                  <q>A Preacher ought not to preache himſelfe, but Chriſt. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Q.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Quarreling, ſtrife, and contention.</head>
                  <q>CHriſtians ought to forbeare and forgiue one another, if be ſo that one haue a quarrell againſt another, euen as Chriſt forgaue vs, for how can we expect forgiueneſſe at Gods hands, if be ſo we our ſelues will not forgiue thoſe that haue offended vs. <bibl>Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. 3. 13.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is good to ſpeake wiſelie, and warily, for oftentimes much coutenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:12040:49"/> quarrelling and debate, ariſeth of a word ill placed, though well meant. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Nuarrell not with one that is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier then thou thy ſelfe art, for he hath the aduantage of thée: might ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth right.</q>
                  <q>There are many who doe nought els but ſowe the ſéedes of quarrels and contentions betwéene neighbours, but Chriſt ſaith; <hi>Bleſſed are the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, for theirs is the kingdome of heauen.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that delighteth in quarrelling, ſhall not want with whom to contend, for rather then he will be quiet, he will be at debate with his owne ſelfe. <bibl>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is better to dwell in a ſmall cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage with a quiet wiſe, then in a ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and ſtately houſe with an vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and quarrelling woman.</q>
                  <q>It is a grieuous thing to dwell with thoſe who when they haue ſayd what they can, and ſpoken the worſt, yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſéeke new occaſions of new
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:12040:49"/> quarrels. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Where ſtriſe, quarrelling and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate are there godly liuing is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>As nothing is more precious in the ſight of God, then loue: ſo nothing is more deſired of the deuill then the quenching thereof, for from thence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe debates contentions quarrellings, fightings, murthers, and many other very haynous and gréeuous ſinnes. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>No roome is large enough for thoſe who cannot well agrée, but a ſmall corner is ſpacious enough vnto thoſe whoſe mindes are vnited by loue and goodwill. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:12040:50"/>
                  <head>Quietneſſe, peace, and tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of minde.</head>
                  <q>THe quietneſſe and tranquility of minde, is more to be eſtéemed then any worldly, wealth whatſoeuer: for what though a man poſſeſſe infinite ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? what though hée want not any outward things that might ſerus for his delight? what are all theſe to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted of, if be ſo thy minde within thée be ſtill tormented with vnquiet thoughts, and diſcontented cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <bibl>Nazianzene.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A guilty conſcience condemneth a mans owne ſelfe, when as no man els accuſeth him: but a cleare conſcience is accompanted with quietneſſe, peace, and tranquility of the minde, when as many falſly accuſe him. <bibl>Hier.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Enough conſiſteth not in the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of wealth, for he that hath a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and a contented minde, hath more then hée that enioyeth much and yet is not contented. <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:12040:50"/>God moſt commonly bleſſeth the poore with quietneſſe, peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of minde, when as yet the ritch though they enioy more, haue leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and tranquility of minde, then the poore haue: and this is one eſpeciall to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Gods goodneſſe towardes the néedy and poore, that he endueth them with ſo much the more ample meaſure of the one, by how much more they are ſcanted of the other. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>By how much more excellent the minde of man is, then his body: by ſo much more are thoſe things that bring content vnto the one, to be eſtéemed, then thoſe things that bring pleaſure vnto the other.</q>
                  <q>By the quietneſſe, peace, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of the minde, the life is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed, but ſorrow, &amp; care haſten death. <bibl>Caſſiod.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is a good thing to liue in quietnes with our neighbours, and friends, and it is a good thing ſo haue reſt and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et from warre with forraine Nations, but it is a more bleſſed thing to haue
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:12040:51"/> quietneſſe and peace, betwéene God and thine owne ſoule.</q>
                  <q>Oftentimes the poore labouring man ceſſeth quietly after his labours, vpon a bed of ſtraw, when as yet the rich mans minde is ſo oppreſſed with cares, &amp; thoughts concerning world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters, that he cannot ſléepe vpon a bed of downe.</q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>R</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Reſurrection.</head>
                  <q>THe iuſt man ſhal ariſe that he may iudge, the vniuſt to be iudged, and the wicked to bee puniſhed without iudgement. <bibl>Caſſius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Our redéemer died that we ſhould not feare death: hee ſhewed his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, that we might haue an aſſured hope of our reſurrection. <bibl>Greg.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>In euery déede and action which a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:12040:51"/> man vndertaketh he hath ſome hope of future commodity: for he that plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth doth it that he may reape. He that fighteth, fighteth that he may ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and to bee without hope of reſurrection, all reſpect of godlines is ſet apart. <bibl>Chriſoſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Some there are who conſidering that the ſpirite leaueth the body: that the fleſh is conuerted vnto rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, rottenneſſe into duſt, and duſt vnto elementes that cannot be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with bodily eyes, doe therefore diſpaire of the reſurrection. And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the dry bones onely iudge it impoſſible that they ſhould againe be couered with fleſh. Who if be ſo they haue not an aſſured hope of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection by obedience: yet ought they aſſuredly to beléeue this by reaſon. For what but the reſurrection rooth the continuall courſe of the elementes declare. For by the courſes of times and ſeaſons wee ſee that trees doe looſe their greene leaues, and likewiſe they doe ceaſe to beare
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:12040:52"/> fruites, and yet ſuddenly as it were out of drie wood we ſée (as if a reſurrection were comming) the leaues to ſpring, the fruites to grow vnto bigneſſe, and the whole trée to be as it were againe cloathed in a freſh garment.</q>
                  <q>Chriſt came into the world, and by his birth, life, words, déedes, paſſions, death, reſurrection, and aſcention, hée fulfilled all the propheſies, and ſayings of the prophets, <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The Sonne of God was in his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tranſlated from his humanity vnto diuinity: in his reſurrection from paſſibility vnto immortalitie: in his aſcention, from low degrée vnto equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity with his Father, becauſe that look<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> how low was his fal from his Fathers boſome vnto the croſſe, ſo high likewiſe might bee his exaltation from the croſſe vnto the right hand of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Let vs waigh with our ſelues the ſmall ſéede of any trée that is caſt into the earth that a trée may procéede there from, and let vs if poſſibly wée
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:12040:52"/> could comprehend, how in ſo ſmall a ſéede ſo great a trée ſhould be incloſed, that there-hence procéedeth. Where is the woode, where the barke, where the gréene leaues, and where the plenty of fruites. Was there any ſuch matters to bee perceiued in the ſéede, when as it lay ouer-couered in the earth? what woonder then is it if ſo it pleaſe God, who is able of ſo ſmall ſéedes to produce ſo great trées, to make againe a man of the ſmall duſt, being conuerted into his proper ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <bibl>Greg.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We that are afflicted and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Chriſtes paſſions, ſhall againe reioyce and be glad in his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</q>
                  <q>It was not by chaunce that the Diſciples, ſeeing the Lorde yet the beloued Diſciple was abſent, but comming afterwarde might heare, and hearing might doubte, and doubting touch, and touching might beléeue. I ſaye it was not done by happe, but that by ſéeing and féeling,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:12040:53"/> he might be made an aſſared witneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of his reſurrection. <bibl>Greg.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Reuerence.</head>
                  <q>REuerence is a vertue whereby we do yéeld vnto our betters, dutyfull regard and reſpect, in the humality of the body, in geſture, behauiour bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the head, and by vtterance of words. <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We cannot adiudge them worthy of reuerence for their honours, whom wee iudge to bée vnworthy of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. <bibl>Boetius.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Reconciliation.</head>
                  <q>HE thinketh vainely who iudgeth that God will bee ſo pleaſed with him, who himſelfe will not be pleaſed with his neighbour. <bibl>Chriſoſtome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>If thou haue offended in thought make amendes and be reconciled in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:12040:53"/> thought: if in words, by wordes, if in déedes, by déedes, for thou canſt not pacifie him whom thou haſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with déedes, without déedes. Thou dooſt fooliſhly to deſire of the Lorde, thou dooſt vainely to giue almes of theſe things which thou haſt ſpoyled others of. For what auaileth it thee if one pray vnto the Lorde for thée, &amp; an other againſt thée, according vnto that in Eccleſiaſtes the 34. The Lord alloweth not the guifts of the wicked.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Riches and rich Men.</head>
                  <q>THoſe are true riches, which being once had cannot be loſt. <bibl>Auguſt. epiſt. 140.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is as hard a thing for a rich man not to bee proude, as it is for a chollericke man not to bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie.</q>
                  <q>Riches are gotten by much labour,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:12040:54"/> trauaile, and paines taking: are kept with continuall care, and left with er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame ſorrow. <bibl>Gregorie.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Moſt commonly the prodigall ſpend, thriſt conſumeth that in ſewe dayes, which his pinchfiſt father ſcraped to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in many yeares.</q>
                  <q>Riches if we come by them iuſtly, and vſe them rightly, are the bleſſings of God, but if we abuſe them they were giuen vs vnto our greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</q>
                  <q>It is an eaſic matter for a man that is rich to ſéeme to deſpiſe riches: but it is a very difficult matter for him that is poore, not to deſire to be riche. <bibl>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie 11. moralium.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is not a ſinke to be riche: but not to diſtribute thereof vnto the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the poore, that is haynous in the ſight of God. <bibl>Chryſoſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Where riches are honoured, good men are deſpiſed.</q>
                  <q>If thou haue plentifull, ſpend nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too prodigally, nor yet kéepe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too niggardly, ſo ſhalt thou be
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:12040:54"/> neither in future time néede, nor yet in bondage vnto thy riches. <bibl>Solon.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is a thing very common that the children of poore and meane men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very wealthy: when as yet the children of rich men decay and come vnto indigencie: which procéedeth partly from hence, that the one becauſe he hath little, is ſparing, and painefull, the other hauing much and not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how it was gotten, ſpendeth prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally, not thinking that euer his wealth wilbe conſumed.</q>
                  <q>He is truely rich whoſe life is ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, &amp; abounding with good workes. <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Repentance.</head>
                  <q>HE that by repentance turneth vnto the Lord, ſhall be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of eternall bliſſe with the Angels in heauen. <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>There are many who are more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to repent, then to ſinne, oh won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull madneſſe. Art thou not aſhamed
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:12040:55"/> of the wound it ſelfe, and yet bluſheſt to haue it bound vp and healed: is not the wound loathſome and ſtincking: hie thée therefore vnto the Surgion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent thée, acknowledge thy ſinnes and ſaye, oh Lorde, I haue ſinned againſt thée, pardon mine iniquities, for I haue done amiſſe. <bibl>Auguſt. de pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>To ſinne and not repent therefore. is a more haynous offence in the ſight of God then was the ſinne it ſelfe. <bibl>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>As the penitent thiefe vpon the croſſe by his example of repentance, and his being receiued vnto mercie, gaue good reaſons vnto many ſinners, that they ſhould not deſpaire of Gods mercies: ſo likewiſe it is to be feared that many preſuming vpon the like grace, doe throw themſelues headlong into dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, not beginning to repent vntill ſuch times that they haue no time of repentance left them.</q>
                  <q>Repentance is deriued as it were of puniſhing, becauſe that man dooth by
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:12040:55"/> repentance as it were puniſh the euill that hee hath committed. For theſe thrée things which by the outwards ſtriking of the breſt are ſignified, to wit the breſt, the hand, and the ſound, denoteth that wée repent vs of thoſe things which wee haue done amiſſe by thought, worde and déede. <bibl>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>S.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Slouth.</head>
                  <q>SLouth is a certaine drowſtneſſe of the minde, whereby any man neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecteth to doe any good things, or to finiſh ought being begunne. <bibl>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Of Idleneſſe no profit, but diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity and loſſe ariſeth: <hi>Eſaw</hi> béeing ſlouthfull loſt the bleſſing of his birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, becauſe he had rather take meat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:12040:56"/> then ſéeke to get it. <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The ſlouthfull man will and will not: he is noted by the name of a ſlouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man who wil willingly raigne with God, but is vnwilling to take paines for God. <bibl>Beda.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Rewards pleaſe him when they are promiſed, but ſpirituall combats terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him when they are commanded.</q>
                  <q>Slouthfull men iudge that nothing can be done, which they themſelues ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not performe, giuing ſentence accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto their owne infirmities For we ſuppoſe thoſe things whereunto we are not accuſtomed, hard and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to be endured. We eſtéeme it a torment to want wine, or to ariſe at the breake of the day, yet are not thoſe things difficult, but we are fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eble and weake.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:12040:56"/>
                  <head>Securitie.</head>
                  <q>IT oftentimes happeneth that he who by the battell of temptation could not be ouercome, hath yet greatly béene damnified by his owne ſecurity. <bibl>Greg.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Security ought to be in our hope, and feare in our conuerſation, that thereby thoſe that ſtriue may be cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and thoſe that are ſecure puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</q>
                  <q>No man ought to liue ſecurely in that life which is called altogeather a temptation, knowing that as of bad he may be made better, ſo contrariwiſe of good he may become worſe. <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Many men by a ſecure careleſneſſe in a ſmall time runne into more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and incurre greater loſſes, then after in all their life long they are able againe to recouer, be they neuer ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant.</q>
                  <q>He that is ſecure in his own buſines, will ſurely be remiſſe in anothers.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:12040:57"/>
                  <head>Scripture.</head>
                  <q>HE hath learned moſt who dooth moſt: but if I performe that which thou declareſt, and thy ſelfe net per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, my déedes doe rather hold off the ſcriptures, then thy ſpéech which thou vainely hableſt. <bibl>Hierome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We ought to vſe the holy Scripture in ſtéed of a looking glaſſe, by correcting that which is amiſſe, concerning thoſe things that are well and decent, and by reducing thoſe things that are in a meane vnto a more perfect order. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The meditation of the Lawe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not ſo much in reading the Scripture, as in executing the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes therein contained. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>If there bee ought in the worlde that maye bee a ſtaye vnto a wiſe man, and may perſwade him (béeing peſtered with the hurlie burlies, and troubleſome turmoyles of this world) to beare all things patiently, that I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly perſwade my ſelfe to be princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally effected by reading &amp; meditating
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:12040:57"/> the holy Scriptures. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We ought neither to ſpeake or doe ought, for which we cannot be warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the holy ſcriptures. <bibl>Baſilius.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Whatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne: but faith commeth by hearing and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by the word of God, therfore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſcriptures all our actions want a true ground which is faith, &amp; ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently al our actions which are not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the holy ſcriptures, are ſinne. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>We maye ſay vnto a man falling from his ſtate: <hi>Let no man wax proud:</hi> and we may ſay vnto a man that is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from his fall. <hi>Let no man deſpaire.</hi> Behould how wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully the ſcripture vſeth the ſelfeſame word to depreſſe the proud, and to exalt the humble. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calleth the proud vnto the ſeare of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and the humble vnto the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of faith. Oh ineſtimable medicine of a ſtrange nature, which being laid af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one &amp; the ſelfeſame order, by preſſing downe dryeth vp the ſwelling humors, and by rayſing vppe infuſeth drye.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:12040:58"/> It terrifieth vs from the fall of euill things, but comforteth vs with our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>T.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Tribulation.</head>
                  <q>BY afflictions and tribulations we looſe earthly things, but by patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſtaining thereof, we multiply heauenly ioyes. <bibl>Greg.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The Lord maketh the way through which his elect are to paſſe vnto him, rough and hard leaſt that being deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the pleaſure thereof, as it were with the ioyes and delicates of this life, they ſhould rather chooſe to linger in their iourney then haſten vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and ſo reſpecting the pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the way, ſhould forget their country whereunto they were going. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>As the ſtarres doe ſhine in the night but are not ſéene in the day time: euen ſo true vertue which oftentimes in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:12040:58"/> is not apparant, yet in aduerſity and tribulation is ſéene moſt euidently. <bibl>Barnard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Be not angry though the wicked floriſh in this world, and the godly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer tribulation, becauſe it is not proper vnto true Chriſtian Religion, to be exalted but to be depreſſed. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked haue no inheritance in heauen, nor the godly in the world: But the godly ought to reioyce in this life with all aſſured hope of their future felicitie in heauen. <bibl>Beda.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Let vs beare patiently ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and croſſes, remembring what he ſuffered for vs vpon the croſſe who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiteth vs vnto that heauenly banket in heauen. <bibl>Caſſi.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>No man knoweth how much he hath profited but in aduerſity: becauſe euery one receiueth the bleſſing of Gods grace in reſt and quietneſſe, but how much he hath receiued is declared onely in the ſufferance of tribulation and aduerſity. <bibl>Greg.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>God is a Phiſition, and tribulation
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:12040:59"/> a medicine for our health, and not a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for our damnation: man comming vnder the hands of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian is tormented, wounded, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out bitterly, but the Phiſitian hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not according vnto his patients minde, but as it may be for his health: euen ſo likewiſe the Lord afflicteth his beloued with tribulations, croſſes, and anguiſhes, that he may bring thoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him by that meanes who otherwiſe would runne headlong into perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Temptation.</head>
                  <q>OVr auncient enemy the deuil cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not euery wher to lay ſnares, that he may weaken the faith of belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers by any meanes whatſoeuer for he knoweth whom to alure with the luſts of the fleſh, into whom to infuſe the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of enuy, and to whome he may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12040:59"/> the alurementes of luxury: hée knoweth whome to vexe with griefe, whom to deceiue with ioy, whome to oppreſſe with feare, and whome to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce with admiration. He prtes into all mens ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners, he winnoweth out as it were their cauſes, he ſearcheth al mens affections, and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence ſéeketh to produce cauſes of their hurt, wherein e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one is moſt buſtly occupted. <bibl>Leo Papa.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The deuill, before he aſſay to tempt any man, firſt diligently waigheth his nature whom he meaneth to tempt &amp; ſo apptieth himſelfe by faire and ſmooth meanes to cauſe a man to offend in that caſe, whereunto he is by nature moſt inclinable: vnto thoſe that are of gentle &amp; milde behauiour, he oppoſeth ryotouſneſſe, and vaine-glory: but vnto thoſe that are of a more ſterne conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be inſtanateth anger pride and cruelty. <bibl>Proſper.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Whiles we breath in this pilgrimage our life cannot bee without ſhine, it
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:12040:60"/> cannot be without temptation: becauſe our p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ogreſſe is made through tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, neither doth any man know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aright valeſſe he be tempted, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he be crowned vnleſſe he ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, neither ouercome without fight, neither can be fight vnleſſe be haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies with whome he may fight. <bibl>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>In all temptations reſiſt the diuell and he will flie from thée, but if thou giue ground vnto him he will purſue thée.</q>
                  <q>The Lord by <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith vnto <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, how long ſhall wicked thoughtes habour in thee,</hi> he aſketh not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come but wherefore they ſtaye: for manye good men are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ouertaken with euil thoughts but yet they will not yéelde their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents thereunto. <bibl>Ambroie.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12040:60"/>
               <head>V.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Vertue.</head>
                  <q>ALl vertues are ſo linked together that he that lace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth one, lacketh all, &amp; he that hath one hath al. <bibl>Hierome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The minde cannot haue vertues kingdome, vnleſſe it firſt ſhake off the kingdome of vices. <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A poore man that hath nothing at all, may be vertuous as well as the rich man, that hath all things in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance.</q>
                  <q>He is endned with many vertues. who loueth vertue in another as well as in himſelfe <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>There can no more perſwaſiue meanes be vſed to purſue v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtue, then the conſideration and remembrance of our owne ſinnes. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Vertue which is conſtrained is not vertues, for that cannot be ſaid to be a vertuous déede (in reſpect of the agent)
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:12040:61"/> which is of neceſſity commanded to be done.</q>
                  <q>What is vertue but a mederine, and what; is vice but a wound, where, as therefore we doe make a wound of the medecine, God maketh a medicine of the wound, that thoſe which are wounded with vertue, might be healed with vice. <bibl>Greg.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Vertue ought to be more eſtéemed of vs then any poſſeſſions, any wealth, and aboundance of earthly, treaſure, or what ſoeuer tranſltory, and momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie riches, becauſe the one remaineth for euer our owne, but the others are no longer ours then whiles we enioy them here in this world: and beſides all goods, wealth, riches, or any earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſiſſion, many be diuers wayes loſt, and are ſubiect vnto many caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but veriuo goeth with vs vnto our graue, and leaueth vs not here, neither in the worlde to come.</q>
                  <q>A good worke man conuerteth all things vnto the beſt vſe that may be, and a veriuous man vndergoeth all
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:12040:61"/> things patiently, and apylyeth euerye thing vnto the furtherance of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</q>
                  <q>Enuie attendeth vpon vertue, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy alwayes to blemiſh her beſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Vowes.</head>
                  <q>ENforced vowes are not to be kept. Better is it not at all to vow then to vow the performance of an euill action: and better is it to breake the performance of a bad vow, then to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute it.</q>
                  <q>Let it not repent thée to haue vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy ſeruice vnto vertue, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reioyce that thou art reſtrayned from that which would incurre thine owne loſſe and hinderaunce. It is an happie neceſſitie which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth vnto better things. <bibl>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:12040:62"/>He is iuſtly enforced to pay that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth of his owne accord fréely. <bibl>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>If thou haue made a wicked vow, breake promiſe therein, and in a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt cauſe alter thy decrée: performe not that which raſhly thou haſt vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: badde is that vow which is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with ſinne, as for example, if raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in thy fury thou haue vowed the death of any man, is it not better that thy vow be broken then kept. <bibl>Iſydore.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>In making a vow firſt conſider whether it be agréeable vnto Gods wil, and next whether thou be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, If both theſe concurre then ſée that thou haue a care diligently to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which ſo iuſtly thou haſt bound thy ſelfe vnto.</q>
                  <q>Miſerable is the ſtate of ſome roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ruffians, who in a brauery or any other wicked humor vow the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of many vile and odious actes, but more miſerable is their eſtates who not onely vow, but more wickedly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which ſo vnaduiſedly they
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:12040:62"/> enterpriſed.</q>
                  <q>If thou haue vowed any good act, delay not the time of performance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for he that is not now apt, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row wilt be more vnapt, and allwaies the longer the doing of good is delayed, by ſo much is it the worſe.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Vice.</head>
                  <q>VIces do firſt poſſeſſe the minde, as it were vnder a ſhew of vertue, or at the leaſt wiſe vnder pretence of ſome colourable reaſon, thereby to ſeeme more tollerable, but hauing once taken poſſeſſion, it groweth vnto an habite, and ſo by cuſtome the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable and odious vices ſeeme toile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table which were they indeede wayed in the ballance of iuſtice, would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly deteſted. <bibl>Hierom.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Euery vice is a ſinne, and euen as cuſtome in ſinning taketh away the feeling thereof, ſo likewiſe the frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of ſome vices make them ſeeme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vitious, no vices. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:12040:63"/>There is a certaine affinity, (as I may ſo ſay) betweene ſome vices, as the diſſolutenes of the ſpirit, the appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tite of the throate, and the beaſt lineſſe of luxurie, much pratling, deceipt, and forſooearing: by the diſſolutneſſe of the ſpirit, the mind is drawen to gurman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, and the belly being crammed with meates, the fleſh is prouoked vnto luſt: By much pratling, deceipt ſteppeth in, becauſe it is a hard matter for him that talketh much, to be voyde of lying, and oftentimes dayly is bound with an oath thereby to deceiue men. <bibl>Greg.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Many are ſo bewitched with thoſe vices that they poſſeſſe, that they will rather enforce arguments to defend them, they be induced by any reaſons to forſake them. <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Vices ſeeme to allure with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, asconeteouſneſſe promiſeth good ſtore of money, rioteouſneſſe maketh ſhe we of many pleaſers, and fleſhie delights: Ambition with braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of apparrell, and the applauſe of the people, and conſequently
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:12040:63"/> of power, and might, and whatſoeuer utay there-from ariſe. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Godly parents haue not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes good children, neither haue wicked parentes allwayes vicious and bad children, as appeareth by holy <hi>Dauid,</hi> who had wicked <hi>Abſolon,</hi> and ſo likewiſe of others who being themſelues bad yet had godly children. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Vice is an inordinate naturall affection, and an act exceeding order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue meaſure, when as it is moued to perpetrate that that ought not to be done, and exceeding meaſure when as it is moued more then it ought. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Forſake not thy friend for one vice, but rather beare with one imperſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if thou can ſt not reclaime him: for <hi>Nemo fine crimine viuit:</hi> there is noe man but hath ſome ſault. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is an exceeding great vice to be prying into the actions of other men and not to regard thine owne, for none but Chriſt could euer rightly
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:12040:64"/> ſay who can accuſe me of ſinne's</q>
                  <q>From the hart of man proceede his thoughts, and moſt commonly ſuch as are the outward actions of the body, ſuch likewiſe are the inward thoughts of the minde, for albeit none but God alone can rightly vnderſtand the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of mans hart, yet the outwarde actions being vicious, a man may iudge that the minde from whence they proceede is likewiſe corrupted, for ſuch as is the trée, ſuch is the fruite likewiſe: and ſuch as is the hart, ſuch likewiſe are the actions, either good or bad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from thence. <bibl>Nazian.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Happie art thou (oh man) who deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending from a vitious ſtocke, art yet thy ſelfe vertuous, for thy vertues do by ſoe much the more ſhine in thee, by how much the more the vices of thy progenitors darkned their glory, and ſpotted their good names. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:12040:64"/>
               <head>W.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Women</head>
                  <q>SAmpſon a couragious &amp; valiant ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrangled a Lion, but he could not bridle his owne loue. He brake his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies bondes, but he could not rule his owne paſſions. He burnt other mens harueſts, but he himſelfe being kindled with a womans loue, loſt the harueſt of his owne vertue. <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Wittily and not vntruly was it an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by one, who being demaunded what was lighter then the fire, ſaid the ſmoke? what lighter then ſmoake? the ayre? what lighter then the ayre? a woman? what lighter then a woman? nothing.</q>
                  <q>What auayleth it thee to watch thy wife ſo narrowly, ſeeing that an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt wife cannot be kept from diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, and an honeſt and chaſt wife no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no cuſtodie. For neceſſitie is an vnfaithfull keeper, but ſhe is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:12040:65"/> chaſte who had libertie to play the harlot and yet would not, and not ſhe that would haue played the ſtrumpet, and yet coulde not.</q>
                  <q>What els is an euill woman but the enemie of amity, an vnauoyda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble puniſhment, a neceſſary euill, a naturall temptation, a deſired ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie an houſhould enemie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> delightfull loſſe, an euill ouerſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with the colour of goodneſſe! Therefore if it be a ſinne to ſendè her packinge, it is a torment to keepe ber, and of neceſſity a man muſt either commit adulterie, or els andure dayly warres, and ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes. <bibl>Chriſoſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Truſt not a woman for her wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, for ſhe will decea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue thee with her teares if thou take not the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heed, teares are vnto women as redie as milke to be drawne out of a new melch cowes teates, they make ſhew of great ſorrow outwardly when inwardly they ar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e no whit greeded: wherevpon aroſe this ſaying. <hi>It is as</hi>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:12040:65"/> 
                     <hi>muchpitty to ſee a woman weepe as it is to ſee a Gooſe go barefooted.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>Better is it to dwell in the corner of an houſe with a quiet woman then in a wids houſe with one that is a ſkoulde.</q>
                  <q>If a Womans will were as much bente vnto goodneſſe, as her witte is apt vnto euill a Prince neede no better counſailers.</q>
                  <q>Wine and Women make men runnagates.</q>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Stockfiſh, a Woman,</l>
                        <l>and a Walenut trèe,</l>
                        <l>The more they are beaten,</l>
                        <l>the better they will bée.</l>
                        <l>Women are wilie,</l>
                        <l>and ſubtill withall,</l>
                        <l>He that ouerreacheth them,</l>
                        <l>is a Man ſtronge and tall.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <q>As by a woman our firſt parent <hi>Adam</hi> was ſeduced to eate of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruite, eauen ſo likewiſe by a woman was the chiefeſt piller of the church who had before confeſſed the ſonne of God, enforced to deny his
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:12040:66"/> Lord and Maiſter.</q>
                  <q>Who is ſo madde as to diſcloſe any ſec<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ret vnto a woman, who only can conceale that which ſhe knoweth not, and nothing elſe.</q>
                  <q>
                     <p>Women when they are met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther keepe a chirping like the parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of birdes: whereof aroſe this two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde ſaying;</p>
                     <l>Many Geeſe much gagling,</l>
                     <l>Many women much babling.</l>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And againe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <l>Many Geſſe many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Many women many wordes.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>A Cage for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ueane, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for a Roague, and a wiſpe for a ſkould, are as fit as meate for the body, cloathes for the backe, or a rod for a wanton boy.</q>
                  <q>A woman if once ſhe take a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke againſt any one is in exorable, and where ſhe hateth ſhe hateth dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</q>
                  <q>A faire woman geuen vnto Iewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is the greateſt temptation that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one can haue, for with her eye the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:12040:66"/> alureth, with her words ſhe enticeth, and with her loue ſhe killeth.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Wiſdome, Foreſight, and Prouidence.</head>
                  <q>THoſe things which many ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming wiſe do approue for exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, being waighed in the ballance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Gods wiſedome, are meerely fooliſh. for the wiſedome of the worlde is foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> with God. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Albeit the aduer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>es of religion do and euer did ſeeke by all meanes poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>une the light of the Goſpel, &amp; to bring groſſe; and palp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble errours into the Church of Chriſt there by in time thanking vtterly to extinguiſh the truth of God, yet are all their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vaine, for the for<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eſeeyng wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God knoweth how to conuert their wicked purpoſes vnto the good of the godly. And albeit they kill and ſtay the conſtant profeſſors thereof, yet hath God appoynted that the blood of the Martirs ſhall be the ſerde of the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:12040:67"/> Church. <bibl>Sanguis Martirum, ſemen eſt eccleſiae.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A wiſe man is ſo tearmed, as it were foreſeeing, for he will prouide for and preuente vncertaine happes. <bibl>Iſidore.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>By the wiſedome and prouidenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of God all thinges are ordayned and that which in mans iudgement can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but fall out to the worſt, yet his wiſedome diſpoſeth it to a good end: and that which we eſteme as a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, God turneth it vnto a medicine. <bibl>Hierome.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A wiſe and foreſeeing man will caſt before hande what his charges and expences are like to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riſe vnto leaſt that running one in an head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe courſe, his purſe be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſcharge the charges that his owne follye hath procured. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A ſodaine miſhappe and vnexper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted is more hardly borne then that which commeth expected, <hi>Nam leuius ledit quicquid preuideris ante.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Cato.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:12040:67"/>Wiſedome iudgeth not of thinges at all aduentares, neither doth it med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with matters not pertayning vnto it: but being brought in as a iudge in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny caſe, it waygheth the reaſons that were the cauſes thereof, conſidereth of the circumſtances inducing therto, and then pronouncing ſentence ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the quallitie of the cauſe ſhall require, there by endenouring that neither ſhe may be rightly accuſed of raſhnes, nor yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> findiſcretion.</q>
                  <q>A man endued with wiſdome ought ſo ranck his actions into three partes, ordering well his actions preſent, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſting for thoſe that are to enſue, and calling to minde thoſe that are paſſed: for be that neuer thinketh of his deeds paſſed deſtroyeth his owne life, and he that foreſéeeth not thoſe to come, falleth at vnawares into many dangers, and inconueniences. <bibl>Senec. de quatuor vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutibus.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Wiſdome, (or prouidence,) is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent knowledge, throughly conſidering &amp; pendering the future euent <bibl>Ibidem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:12040:68"/>
               <head>Y</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Youth.</head>
                  <q>EUen as in old men, ſobriety and perfection of maners is required, ſo likewiſe, ought youth to be obedient, tractable, and willing to learne. <bibl>Cyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>A yong man can hardly be wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that wiſdome is learned by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience which youth hath not tried. <bibl>Ariſtotles Ethicks.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that in his youth hath learned to obay well, is moſt likely in his old age to gouerne well.</q>
                  <q>Youth had need to be vertuouſly treyned vp in time of yongyeares, for how hardely many (who haue in their yonge yeeres had the raine in their owne hands) are reſtrained from thoſe vices which in youth they learned, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience it ſelfe dayly teacheth.</q>
                  <q>Good education formeth manners, and if thy children in their yong age be vertuouſly inſtructed, in thy old-age
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:12040:68"/> they will be a comfort vnto thee, but let them haue their owne will when they are yong, and when thou art old they will not reg<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ard thee.</q>
                  <q>Youth is hotte, becauſe the blood is then mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> freſh, and it is a hard matter in youth to be free from luſt.</q>
                  <q>He that dying rich leaueth his wealth vnto prodigall youth, at the yeares end ſhall haue as many angels in his Coffine as the other hath in his purſe.</q>
                  <q>As it is an excellent thing to ſee youth well murtured, ſo is it a moſt odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing to ſee an old man who is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to goe vnto his graue, voyd of good manners.</q>
                  <q>Vſe no vnſeemly ſpeeches in the preſence of youth, for there by thou thy ſelfe ſhalt be cenſured for vndiſereete, &amp; youth will be eaſily corrupted by thy lewde and Idle communications. For all of vs by nature are more ready and apt to noſe and marke any idle and vaine words then to imitate any godly or vertuous actions.</q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:12040:69"/>If then loue thy childe, in youth giue him correction, for he that ſpareth the rode ſpoyleth the child.</q>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quo prius induta eſt, ſeruabit odorem teſta diù:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Looke with what liquor a veſſel or caſk is firſt filled, and it wil long retaine the ſmel therof, ſo likewiſe youth, &amp;c.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>The headlong courſes of youth cauſe repentance in old age when as experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence telleth vs how vaine a courſe we haue runne. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Youth is vnſtayed, vnconſtant, raſh, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y, and vnaduiſed but when it hath runne his courſe, &amp; ſeeth his owne fully, their beginneth to looke backe vnto the paths that it hath trode, &amp; ſeeketh to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déeme the time miſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, when it hath no time leſt to recouer it. <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is a death vnto youth to be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of his liberty, but when riper iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath taken poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, then it confeſſeth that had not youth ben bridled, old age had been like to goe a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gging.</q>
                  <q>Euen as the Roſe that in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> morning
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:12040:69"/> floriſheth, but in the euening fadeth a way and withereth, euen ſo is the life of man, ſoone ripe ſoone rotten, no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at yeares of vnderſtanding, &amp; iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but preſently enſueth death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtayed experience can haue time to amend the giddie errouts of wanton youth. <bibl>Bernard.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>He that marrieth a child, moſt. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly dyeth a beggar, he that marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for beauty, oftentimes dieth a cuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>old, he that marrieth a ſkould, hath a ſhrewde gooſe to pull, and he that in youth betaketh himſelfe vnto luſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore olde age come ſhall want an hairy buſhe to keepe his braines warme. <bibl>Idem-</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Youth may be compared vnto a fertile ground, wherein whatſoeuer ſéede be ſowen it will proſper, euen ſo youth, if the precepts of vertue and godlineſſe bée ſo wen therein, they will fructifie and growe vnto a good increaſe, and likewiſe if vice be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in planted it will not be barren of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt liuing.</q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:12040:70"/>To late commeth repentance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> old age, when youth hath conſumed the treature that ſhould maintaine thee in thy later yeares.</q>
                  <q>Many in theyr old age and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towardes their death are ſo tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the remembrance of their wicked youth ſpent in vngodlineſſe, that they are all moſt as it were in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of pardon thereof. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Z</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Zeale.</head>
                  <q>IT auayleth nothing to haue the zeale of God without knowledge: the Iewes being blinde thought that they had the zeale of God, yet were they ſacrilegious vnto the ſonne of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, for they being ignorant of the righteouſnes which came by the ſonne of God, thought to cleaue wholye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their owne rightcouſneſſe, and ſo refuſed to ſubmit themſelues vnto the righteouſnes of Chriſt, where vnto they
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:12040:70"/> ought to haue cleaued, <bibl>Origen.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The firſt occaſion of well doing is the commendation of honeſt actions: for praiſe begetteth zeale: zeale procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vertue, and vertue acquireth bliſſe, and this is the principall marke whereat all honeſt mens actions are chiefly bent. <bibl>Nazian.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The zeale of the Lord is a grace which ſearcheth and ouercommeth, yea it infuſeth it ſelfe into the breſt of the righteous. The zeale of God is life. Thoſe that haue the zeale of the Lord. iudge all men that are enemies vnto God to bee theirs alſo, although they be father, mother, brother and ſiſter, <bibl>Ambroſe.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>There is no ſacrifice ſo acceptable vnto the Almighty as is the zeale of ſoules. <bibl>Greg.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Zeale is the feruentneſſe of the mind prone vnto compaſſion of nature, the puniſhment of offences, and the loue of grace and goodneſſe: zeale therefore profitably ſcourgeth a bad ſeruant, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth wholeſome correction vnto a fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:12040:71"/> childe, and carfully obſerueth the bonds of wedlock. The firſt by pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, the ſecond by compaſſion, and the third by loue. <bibl>Hugo.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>The Lord in his zeale will conſume thoſe that walke ſtubbornely after the inuention of their owne hartes. <bibl>Deut. 29. 20.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Bleſſed is the man that is zealous for the Lord of hoaſts ſake, the Lord will requite them with eternall feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie.</q>
                  <q>There is a zeale vnto life, and a zeale vnte death, the zeale vnto life keepeth Gods commandements, and for his name ſake abhorreth to doe euill, ſuch was the zeale of <hi>Phinees.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>The Lord of his mercie grant that we may be all zealous for his ſake, and not ſuffer ſo many abuſes vncontrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as now we do.</q>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="collection">
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:12040:71"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Certaine celected ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> both briefe and pythy.</head>
            <q>THe remembrance of the godly (albeit they returns to earth as other men do) endureth for euer.</q>
            <q>Man doth his endeuoure, but it is God that giueth the iſſue.</q>
            <q>A wiſe man loueth to be admoniſhed; but afoole hateth correction.</q>
            <q>We ought to vſe temporall riches, but not to repoſe confidence therein.</q>
            <q>A ſorrowfull hart pineth the bodie.</q>
            <q>Vnto the godly all thinges ſort vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the beſt.</q>
            <q>We haue all ſinned, and haue all neede of a ſauiour.</q>
            <q>As we are moſt ſure once to die, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are we moſt vnſure when we ſhall die.</q>
            <q>The longer we liue, the more are our croſſes.</q>
            <q>The wicked take counſell together, but God ouerthroweth their purpoſes.</q>
            <q>We ought not to giue ſentence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we haue hard both parties, for one
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:12040:72"/> mans tale is good vntill anothers b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> toulde.</q>
            <q>Mans life is a warfarre, and if he meane to purchaſe heauen, he muſt fight manfully againſt the worlde, the fleſh and the deuill.</q>
            <q>To care for the body only and to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the ſoule, is the right way to the deuill.</q>
            <q>God depreſſeth the proud, but ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth grace vnto the lowly and méeke.</q>
            <q>Deſpiſe not the poore for we are all Gods creatures.</q>
            <q>He that taketh councell againſt the Lord, ſtriueth againſt the ſtreame.</q>
            <q>Deſpaire not in afflictions, for ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God trieth thy faith.</q>
            <q>As is a blubbe vpon the water, euen ſo is the life of man, to day a man to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morrow none.</q>
            <q>Where Iudges are corrupted with bribes, there the poore goe home by wéeping croſſe.</q>
            <q>The lawier and the leache may well be compared, for the leache neuer hath inough till his belly breake, nor the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:12040:72"/> lawier vntill he want breath.</q>
            <q>He that goeth to law for euery tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle, will helpe to make the lawier rich &amp; himſelfe a beggar.</q>
            <q>He that maketh himſelfe beho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ldinge vnto his enemie, ſelleth his owne liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</q>
            <q>A fayned trend is more daingerous then aproſeſſed ſoe.</q>
            <q>He that thinketh to get any thing out of the courtous mans purſe, is as much deceaued, as he that thinketh to wring water out of a ſtone.</q>
            <q>Eate not ouer much for cloying thy ſtomacke.</q>
            <q>Féede not ouer faſt, leſt thou ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle thy ſelfe againſt thy will.</q>
            <q>Faſt not ouer long, leaſt euill ſmels annoy thy ſtomacke.</q>
            <q>As neere as thou canſt!, obſerue a diet, for it is healthfull for thy body.</q>
            <q>Obſerue due ſeaſons in taking thy meate, for then thy appetite moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly will be ſharpe ſet.</q>
            <q>Plenty (of the choyſeſt daynties) is no dainty.</q>
            <q>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:12040:73"/>If thou deſire to haue well, do well.</q>
            <q>He that is in pouertie, and aſketh of one that hath as much neede as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, may goe to bed hungrie, and he that being vnſéene in any matter, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth councell of one that hath as little ſkill as himſelfe, may ſeeke about for a foole, and finde him in his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</q>
            <q>Beauty is like vnto a pleaſant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> flowre which in the morning floriſheth, but in the euening is dryed away and withered.</q>
            <q>He that by wiſedome guideth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſhall receiue glory for his reward, but he that ſuffereth himſelfe to be led by folly, ſhame ſhall be his ending.</q>
            <closer>Naſcimur in commune bonum.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12040:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
